<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prophane schisme of the Brovvnists or separatists With the impietie, dissensions, levvd, and abhominable vices of that impure sect. Discouered by Christopher Lavvne, Iohn Fovvler, Clement Sanders, Robert Bulvvard. Lately returned from the companie of M. Iohnson, that wicked brother, into the bosome of the Church of England, their true mother.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857091</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22763</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 804:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prophane schisme of the Brovvnists or separatists With the impietie, dissensions, levvd, and abhominable vices of that impure sect. Discouered by Christopher Lavvne, Iohn Fovvler, Clement Sanders, Robert Bulvvard. Lately returned from the companie of M. Iohnson, that wicked brother, into the bosome of the Church of England, their true mother.</title>
                  <author>Lawne, Christopher. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for Walter Burre],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XII. [1612]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22763:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PROPHANE SCHISME OF THE BROWNISTS OR SEPARATISTS. WITH THE
JMPIETIE, DISSENSIONS, LEVVD, AND ABHOMINABLE Vices of that impure Sect.</p>
            <p>Diſcouered by 
<list>
                  <item>CHRISTOPHER LAVVNE,</item>
                  <item>IOHN FOVVLER,</item>
                  <item>CLEMENT SANDERS,</item>
                  <item>ROBERT BVLVVARD.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Lately returned from the Companie of M. IOHNSON, that wicked
Brother, into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church of ENGLAND, their true Mother.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 83.16.</bibl> 
               <p>Fill their faces with ſhame, that they may ſeeke thy name, O
Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <bibl>ROM. 16.17.</bibl> 
               <p>Now I beſeech yee, brethren, marke them diligently, which
cauſe diuiſion and offences, contrarie to the doctrine which ye haue
learned and auoid them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>M.D.C.XII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22763:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22763:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO THE CHRISTIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER, TOVCHING THE cauſes
and the maner of our publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hideth his ſins ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper; but hee
that confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall haue mercie,</hi> Prou.
28.13. Our ſin of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereby we haue reiected the communion of all
true Churches, being now made manifeſt vnto vs vpon ſuch occaſion as is
hereafter declared in this Treatiſe, and we deſiring to receiue mercie from
the Father of mercies, haue therefore reſolued and thought in our ſelues,
according to the counſell of the holy Ghoſt, that we will not hide our
iniquitie, but confeſſe againſt our ſelues our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto the
Lord, that the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſin may be forgiuen vs. Our owne
ignorance, and the deceit fulnes of others had drawne vs into the depth of this
error; and in the middeſt of this deepe Schiſme, when the Lord might
iuſtly haue iudged and rebuked vs in wrath, euen then were wee bold to iudge
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne <pb facs="tcp:22763:3"/> others that were better than our ſelues, and farre
excelling vs in all the gifts and graces of Gods Spirit; wee condemned them and
ſlandered our whole nation as a falſe Church, falſe Chriſtians, a
Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan, and a people according to their publike profeſſion in
a damnable eſtate; we exempted none, neither the learnedeſt and godlieſt
Miniſters, nor zealouſeſt people, but condemned all, and auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all in
the ſeruice of God: And therefore to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh our repentance for this
ſcandalous Separation, we hold it in the firſt place a iuſt and
neceſſarie cauſe for the publiſhing of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that is firſt in his owne cauſe is iust; then commeth
his neighbour and maketh enquirie of him;</hi> Prou. 18.17. Maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his confederates being parties accuſed by vs, and
being iudges alſo in their owne cauſe, haue firſt condemned vs with their
cenſure; when we complained of their ſinne, they could find no way to
cleare themſelues but by accuſing vs, ſo that when wee renounced their
Schiſme, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced their curſe againſt vs, and thus declared vs to
be their enemies, when wee told them the truth. In this caſe the holy Ghoſt
alloweth vs to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie for our ſelues, in enquiring into, and
refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe ſlanders which they lay vpon vs, and make the ground of
their ſentence againſt vs. They haue condemned vs firſt in their owne
Church. Wee do now in the ſecond place by a publike appeale bring the matter
before the Churches of Chriſt, to iudge thereof. This is alſo another
cauſe of our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at this time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22763:3"/>
               <hi>When thou art conuerted, ſtrengthen thy
brethren;</hi> Luke 22.32. Being our ſelues deliuered from this ſnare of
the Separation, our deſire is to ſtretch out a hand of helpe and comfort
vnto thoſe, that yet lie in that ditch: and wee are not without hope of
ſome fruit of our endeuours this way; but eſpecially our hope is to ſtay
and ſtrengthen ſome weake Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that are inclining and looking that
way, whom we admoniſh and deſire them in the Lord that they would bee
warned by our harmes, and by our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſtray, to walke the more
circumſpectly in the middeſt of all offences and ſcandals wherewith they
ſhall meete. As for thoſe that are alreadie ſeparate and caught in the
briars of that Schiſme, although we do aſſure our ſelues vpon good
ground, that ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie of them do wiſh they had neuer met with the
Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paration, and would alſo much reioyce if they were well quit and freed
from the ſame, yea and haue wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome of them that there might be a
diſſolution of their ſchiſmaticall bodie, that ſo they might eſcape
without excommunication; yet are they in the meane time kept vnder in ſuch
bondage by the terror, tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, &amp; ſubtiltie of their guides, which they
ſhew both in their doctrine and in their gouernment, that they dare not
eaſily whiſper or muffe againſt the ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As for thoſe whoſe
feet are almoſt gone, &amp; their ſteps wel neere ſlipt, we deſire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
to pauſe a while; it is not ſo eaſie a matter to come out of that ſnare
when they are fallen therein, as it is to keepe out at firſt, &amp; for the
ſtay of ſuch we haue thought it needfull to publiſh this Treatiſe for
their further information touching <pb facs="tcp:22763:4"/> the eſtate of
<hi>Browniſme,</hi> as alſo to warne all ſuch as haue bin the occaſion
of thoſe Hereſies and Schiſmes to conforme themſelues to the Church of
God, that theſe Caterpillers may no more riſe out of them.</p>
            <p>And although we be vnlearned men which haue compoſed this booke,
yet we hope it will not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked therefore, ſeeing we ſpeake of nothing
but which our owne knowledge and experience hath taught vs; and the admonition
may take better place, becauſe that the moſt which are taken in the net of
<hi>Browniſme</hi> are men of our condition.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:22763:4"/>
            <head>¶ A Table of the principall matters contained in this
Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The firſt Section.</head>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Chapter 1.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Declaration of our procedings with
Master <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and the Elders in publique in their Meeting-houſe.
<hi>Folio 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> A copie of <hi>Chriſtopher Lawnes</hi>
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication: with an anſwer thereunto. <hi>fol. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> A copie of <hi>Iohn Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> his excommunication: with an
anſwer thereunto. <hi>fol. 12</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond Section.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter 1.</hi> A True relation of the Schiſme,
Diſſenſions, Blasphemies, Hereſies, and horrible crimes practiſed by
the <hi>Browniſts</hi> or Separators. <hi>fol. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> The testimony of father <hi>Tolwine</hi>
against theyr iniustice, ſchiſme and ſlaunder. <hi>fol. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> The copie of <hi>Robert Bulwards</hi>
ſuspenſion and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>communication: with an anſwer thereunto. <hi>fol.
20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> A relation of <hi>Studley</hi> his
wickedneſſe tranſlated out of the Dutch. <hi>fol. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22763:5"/>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> A diſcouerie of ſome of the
abhominations of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> in Amsterdam. <hi>fol. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> A compariſon betweene two notable
Separatists, <hi>Daniel S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>dley,</hi> and <hi>Richard Mansfield. fol. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap 7.</hi> The testimony of <hi>William Gilgate,</hi>
one of Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Ainſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth his
company, and one that had beene Minister in England. <hi>fol. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Letters that paſſed betwixt Maister
<hi>Ames</hi> and Maister <hi>Robinſon</hi> touching the bitterneſſe of
the Separation. <hi>fol. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> A relation of the hereſie of <hi>Thomas
Lemar. fol. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> The testimonie of <hi>William
Simpſon</hi> against the Prophets in Maister <hi>Amſworth</hi> his Church.
<hi>fol. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Of the diſſenſion betweene <hi>Iohn
Iohnſon</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>Francis</hi> the ſonne: and betwixt the
brothers, <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Francis. fol. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> A taste of their deteſtable ſlaunders
and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches concerning the Church of England. <hi>fol. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Concerning their mutuall reproches,
diſſenſions, and curſes against one an other. <hi>fol. 70.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <head>This Booke is diuided into two Sections.</head>
            <p>THE firſt containeth ſuch matters as paſſed betweene
theſe foure perſons <hi>Christopher Lawne, &amp;c.</hi> and the Sect of
Maiſter <hi>Iohnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Section containeth a true relation of the Schiſme,
Diſſenſions, Blaſphemies, Hereſie, and horrible Crimes practiſed by
theſe <hi>Brownists</hi> or Separatiſts.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22763:5"/>
            <head>¶ THE PROPHANE SCHISME OF THE BROWNISTS OR SEPARATISTS.
The firſt Section.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. A declaration of our proceedings with maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and the Elders in publike, in their meeting-houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing formerly refuſed to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Conſiſtorie
in maſter <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> houſe, in reſpect of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
abuſe, ſcorne, and other iniury, which there they offered vnto vs; at
length they conſented to ſend for vs vnto their publike Aſſemblie,
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had long denyed the ſame vnto vs, who many times had ſought
it of them, that there we might make a publike renunciation of our
vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſeparation, which we with them had vndertaken, from all the
Churches of Chriſt; to trie alſo whether it might pleaſe the Lord to
touch the hearts of ſome others, and to giue them repentance likewiſe by
our example. And thus <pb n="2" facs="tcp:22763:6"/> the ninth of Iuly 1611. being
accompanied with diuers ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and members of the Engliſh Church, vnto
which wee haue now ioyned our ſelues, wee came vnto them in their
meeting-houſe, after their euening exerciſe was ended.</p>
               <p>Being come vnto them, and ſtanding in the middeſt of them,
the notorious <hi>Daniell Studley,</hi> maſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> chiefe
Standard bearer, beeing for that day the Proloquut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of their Company, beganne firſt to make a Speech to
the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to relate vnto them, How we had charged them to be
Schiſmatikes in the ſeparation from England, and to be a profane people;
and that we had nominated one woman to be profane, and that we refuſed to
prooue the ſame; that we had refuſed to come vnto their Elderſhip; that
wee had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen diuers Articles againſt them, which we refuſed to proue
&amp;c. And that now therefore they required anſwer for theſe things.
<hi>Daniel Studley</hi> hauing ended his Speech: we in the next place deſired
leaue to ſpeake ſome things vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, before wee gaue anſwere in
particular vnto the Speech of <hi>Daniell Studley;</hi> eyther for iuſtifying
of thoſe things that were truely ſpoken, or for the reproofe of thoſe
things that were falſe. And ſo in the firſt place wee acknowledged our
ſinne in the ſeparation which we had made from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt:
wee acknowledged the great mercy of the Lord, that had ſo graciouſly giuen
vnto vs to ſee our errors, into which we had bin led by the falſe doctrines
of M. <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and others: wee acknowledged the mercy of God, that
had giuen vs hearts carefull in ſome meaſure to manifeſt and ſhew forth
the fruits of our repentance, both to the Lord &amp; to his people; and that,
both by word and writing as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould be offered: We ſignified
vnto them, that as wee had done it more priuatly before their Elders: ſo now
in the preſence of them all, with whome together we had beene ſo deepely
plunged into the gulfe of ſchiſme; wee did openly renounce our couenant and
profeſſion of ſeparation, which at our firſt entrance among them we had
made with them: we renounced it, as being a moſt abhominable and profane 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22763:6"/> thing, againſt which the Lord had manifeſted his anger
from heauen, as agenſt a Babilonious tower which the Lord would haue to bee
brought to naught, as appeared by the manifold confuſions and
diſſipations among them: we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed further vnto them, that as we
had bin inſtruments for the ſtrengthening and vpholding of that Tower of
Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo we did purpoſe by Gods aſſiſtance, to vſe our
beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours to bring downe the ſame into the duſt: And laſtly we
teſtified vnto them, that we came not vnto them at this time by virtue of
power or authority that they had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand vs, but in the bowels of mercie
&amp; tender compaſſion towards them; hoping God would be gracious vnto
ſome of them, at the leaſt to plucke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth as firebrands out of this
fire, as the Lord had therein dealt mercifully with vs.</p>
               <p>In the next place, touching that which was obiected by <hi>Da.
Studley,</hi> we anſwered, That he had not rightly repeated our charge. Our
charge was; that they were ſchiſmatiks; that they were profane in their
ſchiſme; that it led them to the breach of all Gods commaundements; And
that thus they had it in writing vnder our hands; And that theſe things
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proued, their ſeparation from England would hereupon appeare to be
vnlawfull. Againe, as for that particular wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man nominated by vs for a profane
perſon, we refuſe not to proue the ſame; yet deſire we, that firſt of
al this foule lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of profane ſchiſme, imputed vnto you all, may be
cleered by you, if you can. According to the counſell you gaue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we
require you, firſt to plucke this great beame out of your eies, &amp; then
ſhal you the better ſee to help this poore woman.</p>
               <p>Vnto this anſwer made by vs, <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> replied
not; but then flew in vpon vs M. <hi>Francis Iohnſon</hi> himſelfe. The
firſt word he ſpake was a reproch; the ſecond railing alſo; the third
was a lie; the fourth was a word of tyranny. The firſt title he gaue was
Hypocrite; the ſecond was railing <hi>Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites;</hi> the third, he
ſaid our charge was for England in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and fourthly, he ſaid he
would hold vs to that charge. <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22763:7"/> And for the matter of
profaneneſſe, he would firſt haue that particular woman to be ſo
proued. If his power had bin ſo great, as his impotent paſſion, what
would he not haue done to vs? M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> would not yet in any ſort
meddle with the defence of his doctrine; but inſtead thereof he turned
aſide, &amp; entred into a long diſcourſe touching the eſtate of
diuerſe Churches in ſeueral ages. The ſumme of his ſpeech was this.
Hauing ſhewed how all the world was drowned in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme, he
then told them how it pleaſed God in the firſt place to raiſe vp <hi>Iohn
Huſſe,</hi> and ſuch like, to witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the groffeſt
euills in their times; then hee tolde how <hi>Martin Luther</hi> came
afterwards, by whom a further refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was obtained; then in the next place
he ſhewed how they of England had gone many degrees before eyther of the
former: Aboue all theſe hee ſhewed in the next place, how M.
<hi>Caluine</hi> had been an inſtrument of greater light, and reformation, in
a higher degree than any of the forenamed, though ſtil in many things
corrupt; but laſt of all, and aboue all, in the higheſt degree of
perfection hee placed his owne company, preferring the bright eſtate of his
Church aboue al the golden Candle ſticks that euer Chriſt walked amongſt,
ſince the days of reformation. He affirmed openly, that they were by the
mercie of God the pureſt Church, and the freeſt from corruptions, and ſet
in a more excellent order, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Church that he knew this day in the world;
and therfore blamed vs for leauing them, &amp; going into a corrupter eſtate.
Thus did hee exalt himſelfe and his diſciples, as though hee had been the
brighteſt ſtarre in the fimament, aboue <hi>Huſſe, Luther,
Caluine,</hi> or the Martires of England; and ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, as though
<hi>Daniell Studley, Edward Benet, Canadine Mercer, Christopher Bowman,</hi>
and <hi>Iacob Iohnſon,</hi> with the reſt, the wandering Starres of their
ſchiſmaticall companie, had likewiſe excelled <hi>Beza, Morney, Iunius,
Zanchius, Brad ford, Perkins, Whitakers,</hi> and ſuch like burning lamps,
whoſe light hath ſo comfortably ſhined abroad: whereas (indeed) M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> might with farre better reaſon haue more fitly 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22763:7"/> compared himſelfe and his fellowes vnto <hi>Menno Simons,
Derick Philips, Hans-de Rees,</hi> and ſuch other Authors of
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtrie, who alſo haue gone before him in teaching all or the moſt
of the verie ſame points, wherein he profeſſeth himſelfe to differ from
the reformed Churches; as in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars may eaſily be ſhewed when
time ſerueth.</p>
               <p>After this, maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> tooke maſter
<hi>Parkers</hi> booke written againſt the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and by a
large and impertinent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe begin to ſhew how many corruptions and
ſins were committed, and maintained in the Church of England. And hereupon we
ſignified vnto him, how vainely and idly hee ſpent his time in labouring to
draw vs from the maine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the charge which wee had laid vpon them,
touching their ſchiſmaticall and falſe doctrine, taught by him, and
<hi>H. Barrow</hi> before him. And to the examination of this doctrine, we
required him to come to the examination of that their falſe doctrine
wherewith we had charged them; but he ſtill refuſed, hauing been more then
ſeuen times vrged thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as many witneſſes can well teſtifie. His
deſire was ſtill to wrangle about their practiſe, and to diſpute of
corruptions.</p>
               <p>When maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> could not this way faſten any
blame vpon vs, he then ſought to reproue vs for going vnto maſter
<hi>Padget,</hi> and for talking with him. And heere (certainly) it is needfull
to obſerue their pollice this way; for holding of thoſe in bondage whom
they haue once ſeduced. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure that their members ſhould aske
counſell of any learned man, or confer with any other touching their doubts,
except it be with their owne guides and teachers, or ſome among themſelues.
And therefore when diuers of them knew, that we went to confer with maſter
<hi>Padget,</hi> they were diſpleaſed with vs; they reproued vs; and for
iuſtifying of their reproofe they abuſed (as their manner is) ſundry
points of Scripture; alleaging vnto vs, 
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.7.</note>
                  <hi>That the
Priests lips ſhould preſerue knowledge; that they ſhould ſeeke the law
at his mouth: for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hostes.</hi> This they
allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as though there had been no lippes, of knowledge but 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22763:8"/> only in their company; as though maſter
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and maſter <hi>Clifton</hi> had been the alone Angels of
the Lord of Hoſtet; as though the Law of God were to be ſought for only at
their mouth, and the mouth of <hi>Daniel Studley, Iacob Iohnſon,</hi> the
Prophet <hi>Peckſall,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>It is a miſerie vnſpeakable to be ſeparate from the
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of all true Churches, and to be ſhut out from any other Teachers
whatſoeuer beſides their owne; but yet is it a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bondage to be
reſtrained from priuate conference with other learned men, and ſo to be
depriued from the fruit of their counſell. For this cauſe there are
iuſtly come vpon them all the iudgements that are heere threatened vnto the
deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of counſell. We ſee they fall daily from the Truth, from the
Churches of <hi>Christ,</hi> from themſelues and their owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, from
their owne followers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. A Copie of <hi>Chriſtopher Lawnes</hi>
excommunication with an anſwere thereunto.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hiles we continued conſtantly in the renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of their
ſchiſme and ſeparation; and their Elders on the other ſide as
obſtinately deſpiſing our reproofe of their ſin; they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that
ſundrie of their members began more and more to be troubled, and to doubt of
their eſtate. And therefore to withdraw their members from conuerſing with
vs, and to make good their owne proceedings, and hold on their courſe
againſt vs, they reſolued together to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate vs. Which being done,
and we often deſiring co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of our excommunication, at laſt they gaue
them vnto vs in writing; after this manner.</p>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="excommunication">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Chriſtopher Lawne</hi> was proceeded against by
the Church, the eight and twentieth of the ſeuenth moneth, Iuly, 1611. for
railing, ſlandering, abuſing, and despiſing the Gouernours and 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22763:8"/> whole Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as he manifested by word and
deed, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and otherwiſe: among which were theſe and the like
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                           <p>
                              <label type="milestone">
                                 <seg type="milestoneunit">charge </seg>1</label> That he charged vs to be
ſchiſmatikes for our ſeparation from the Church of England: and hereupon
alſo to be a prophane companie.</p>
                           <p>
                              <label type="milestone">
                                 <seg type="milestoneunit">charge </seg>2</label> Alſo he being a member
of this Church, which by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God hath forſaken the Apoſtaſie
of Antichriſt, and to our knowledge and power witnes againſt all the
corruptions and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations thereof, labouring daily to proceed in that which
is good, for keeping the commandements of God and faith of Chriſt, and to
walke in the ancient way preſcribed the Church by the Lord in his word; yet
did he leaue communion with vs, and diſclaimed our profeſsion, and
accuſed vs to be ſchiſmatikes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is aforeſaid.</p>
                           <p>
                              <label type="milestone">
                                 <seg type="milestoneunit">charge </seg>3</label> Moreouer in a letter
ſent into England hee wrote diuers ſlanders of the Elders and brethren, as
appeareth in the ſaid letter.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>1</label> Firſt, where they write that
<hi>Chriſtopher Lawne</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt by the Church; let it be
remembred that the Church hath ſo done it, that diuers members of that ſame
Church haue acknowledged that they did not conſent vnto that his
excommunication; ſome being abſent when it was done, and ſome ſpeaking
againſt it; and ſome diſliking it; ſome going away at that preſent
becauſe they would haue vs hold it, though not daring to ſpeake againſt
it, as they haue confeſſed ſince vnto vs: and do therfore ſtill
profeſſe as much loue and fellowſhip with vs as formerly they haue
done.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>2</label> Secondly, whereas they write thus
in <hi>the ſeuenth moneth, Iuly,</hi> and againe, 
<note n="a" place="margin">In the copie of <hi>Iohn Fowlers</hi>
ezcommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> 
                  <hi>in the eight moneth, Auguſt;</hi> why might not
they haue written <hi>Iuly</hi> or <hi>Auguſt</hi> alone, without that
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and idle addition of the <hi>ſeuenth</hi> moneth, and the
<hi>eighth</hi> moneth? as well as they wrote ſince 
<note n="b" place="margin">Narration, pag. 1.2.</note> the twentie
ninth of May: September the fourth: the fiue and twentieth of Auguſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>3</label> Thirdly, whereas they obiect vnto
vs <hi>railing, ſlandering, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22763:9"/> abuſing</hi> and
<hi>despiſing,</hi> for the ground of our excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As for their
Gouernors; their eldeſt Elder, and the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt pillar of their
ſeparation ought now to be thruſt our of his gouernment; ſo that their
owne former doctrine, and their preſent endeuours cries ſo loud, and opens
ſo wide a mouth againſt their gouernment, that all their Elders eares may
tingle to eare the ſame. And as for their <hi>whole Church,</hi> whereof they
ſpeake: when it was whole; what is but a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie of a few Schiſmatickes
that had forſaken the Church of God? But now, being diuided in the middeſt,
and halfe of them againe being rent from the other, they might better haue
ſpoken of their <hi>peece,</hi> then their <hi>whole:</hi> they being but the
broken fragment of a ſchiſme. And yet this broken <hi>peece</hi> exalts it
ſelfe aboue all the whole Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">objection </seg>1</label>
                  <hi>That he charged vs to be
Schiſmatikes for our ſeparation from the Church of England; and hereupon
alſo to be a prophane company,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>1</label> As for the ſchiſme and
prophaneneſſe hereupon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee charged them, our proofes touching
both theſe points are ſet downe in the copie of our charge. If maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> had anſwered thoſe grounds of holy Scripture which there
are ſpecified for the maintenance of our Charge, hee might then haue had
ſome colour for this his accuſation: but vntill this be done, or vntill he
repent thereof, the blame and ſhame of thoſe iniquities muſt reſt vpon
his head, and lodge in his boſome. And he might as well vant, the rebukes of
ſinne by the Prophets to be railings and ſtanders, ſince all that we haue
there affirmed in our Charge is warranted and iuſtified by the word of God,
which wee haue expreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let it be obſerued, that they might as wel charge
the holieſt and learnedeſt men in all the Churches of God at this day to be
ſlanderers and railers, as vs; ſeeing they do ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally hold ſuch
doctrine, as we charged them withall, to be falſe and ſchiſmaticall;
ſeeing they do all agree with vs herein. If any of their poore people thinke
it to be otherwiſe, <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22763:9"/> being deceiued by their guides; wee
dſire them to goe vnto them with vs, and to heare their iudgement for
confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereof.</p>
               <p>The ſecond particular here obiected againſt vs, is <hi>for
lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their Communion.</hi> Of this particular onely they giue a reaſon,
taken from the holineſſe and lawfulneſſe of their Communion, to prooue
that we ſhould not haue left them. The weakeneſſe and inſufficiencie of
this their defence may appeare diuers wayes. But let this one ſuffice.</p>
               <p>What hath maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> here ſaid for
himſelfe, which maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> might not as truely alleadge
for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? Maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his people profeſſe
themſelues as great enemies to Antichriſt and his abhominations, as M.
<hi>Iohnſon.</hi> And his profeſſion alſo hath as much ſhew of
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, as that of M. <hi>Iohnſon.</hi> And yet M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi>
witneſſeth againſt them, as againſt a falſe church; teacheth that
their Communion ought to be left, in reſpect of their ſchiſme from him.
And why then may not wee for the ſame reſpect of ſchiſme leaue M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> alſo? Or is it a greater ſinne for M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> to leaue the Communion of M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> than for
maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> to refuſe and auoyde the Communion of all true
Churches beſides?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, where it is ſaid that <hi>to their knowledge and
power they witnes &amp;c.</hi> this appeares to be falſe, and they are not to
be credited herein. Their owne words, and their owne dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, will prooue
their diſſimulation and hypocriſie herein. For when complaint was made to
maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> of their corrupt maner of worſhip in ſinging
their new rithmes: M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> acknowledged that he had ſundry
yeeres together diſliked the ſame; yet neuer witneſſed againſt the
ſame. Yea after this admonition and confeſſion he is ſtil ſilent, and
therefore he doth not according to his knowledge &amp; power witnes againſt
knowne corruptions. For when formerly complaint hath beene made vnto maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> of their naughtie order in ſinging Pſalmes in ſuch a
meeter, and in ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime, as it
ſeems they are aſhamed that any ſhould ſee <pb n="10" facs="tcp:22763:10"/> them to
examine them; (for they keep them among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like a traditionall
myſterie, that few or none, euen of their own people, haue any vſe of them,
ſaue when they are read after a broken maner in publike) when diuerſe
reaſons were alleaged againſt them by ſome of vs; as that they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
not for edification in their publike, being of ſo harſh &amp; hard a
phraſe that they knew not what they meant, neyther could ſing with
vnderſtanding. Secondly, that theſe once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vſe, and copies
thereof kept from the people, by this meanes ſinging of Pſalmes was ſhut
out of priuate houſes, and the comfort thereof loſt amongſt them.
Thirdly, that by the vncouth and ſtrange tranſlation &amp; meetre vſed in
them, the congregation was made a laughing ſtocke to ſtrangers, that by
occaſion came in to ſee them in their publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. When theſe
things were thus related to M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> he acknowledged that he
alſo did diſlike their order, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it, but he did not witnes
againſt it: Indeed <hi>D. Stud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley</hi> pleaded for the vſe of them ſtill
in that order againſt M. <hi>Iohnſon.</hi> And what wonder, that he which
had ſuch a veine in making filthy and obſcene rithmes, which he taught
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to little children? or that his Client miſtris <hi>M. Maie,</hi> the
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualler, who vſed in her houſe to ſing ſuch Songs as is a ſhame
to report, (being more fit for a common bawd, than for a perſon
profeſſing ſuch pure ſeparation from other Churches) as hath bin openly
teſtified in their publike mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-houſe by her owne ſeruant that is one
of them? what wonder if they ſhould bee content to looſe the daily vſe of
ſpirituall Songs and Pſalmes, which cannot dwell together with ſuch
carnall vanitie and vncleane rithmes?</p>
               <p>Againe, he hath of late affirmed, That euery man ought to bring
vp the tenth part of that which hee getteth by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in his ſeuerall
calling, to the maintenaunce of their Church; and that euerie one, which doth
it not, is a thiefe. But ſeeing now he is not like to perſwade his people
to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this doctrine of Extortion, he is content to holde his peace. And
doth he not now willingly ſuffer a company of <pb n="11" facs="tcp:22763:10"/> theeues
(in his accompt) among them? Is not his company become a denne of thieues,
whileſt he winkes with his eies, and doth not daily witnes againſt their
theft, according to <hi>his knowledge and power;</hi> as here he
pretendeth?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">objection </seg>3</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>
                  </label> As
for the third obiection of the Letter; There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it but truth, and
ſuch things as had bin before open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtified vnto them. And ſo it was
ſignified vnto maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> by ſome of their own members at
the reading ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that it was vaine and idle to ſeeke matter againſt
<hi>Christ. Laune,</hi> ſeeing he had himſelfe ſaid much more before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
all.</p>
               <p>But who be thoſe two ſubſcribers, that ſet their hands
to this excommunication? Theſe two be the two ſpecial cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of the
Franciſcan ſchiſme, the two principall pillars of that rotten
ſeparation; the one by his wit, and the other by his wealth. <hi>Dan.
Studley</hi> by his wit and policy hath often turned good into euil, and euill
into good, and brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a man to repentance for well-doing; and therefore
he ſits next vnto S. <hi>Francis</hi> himſelfe in the vſurped throne of
their iudgement, and eftſoones vpon ech occaſion he whiſpers in S.
<hi>Francis</hi> eare, who bends &amp; liſtens to him, to the griefe of many
a perſon that yet remaines in the ſame ſchiſme with them.</p>
               <p>But if any would further know what this <hi>Dan. Studley</hi>
is, let them aske <hi>Samuel Fuller</hi> a Deacon of maſter
<hi>Robinſons</hi> Church, and deſire to ſee a copie of the letter which
<hi>Daniell Studley</hi> ſent vnto him; or let them aske maſter
<hi>Thorpe</hi> a dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> Church, and
deſire to ſee a booke intituled, <hi>The firſt part of the hunting of the
Fox,</hi> and there he ſhall ſee <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> traced vp and downe.
He had a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Palſie in his filthy fiſt, when he ſubſcribed the
copie of this vniuſt excommunication. Had S. <hi>Francis</hi> neuer a
clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fiſt to ſtrike vs withall, than this hand of <hi>Daniel
Studley!</hi> Could he haue done vs a greater comfort, than to declare our
condemnation by that hand, which by the beſt among themſelues is condemned
aſwell as by vs?</p>
               <p>As for this <hi>Edward Benet,</hi> he is to be conſidered as a
<hi>horne <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22763:11"/> of the beast,</hi> that lends his power, wealth,
and authoritie to the maintenance of the beaſt, according to that in the
Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation 17.13. ſo that it is not vnfittely ſpoken by ſome of maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> company, viz. <hi>As the King of Spaine is vnto the Pope:
ſo is Master</hi> Benet <hi>vnto Master</hi> Iohnſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. A Copie of <hi>Iohn Fowler</hi> his
excommunication: with an anſwere thereto.</head>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="excommunication">
                           <p>
                              <hi>
                                 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Fowler</hi> was proceeded againſt by the
Church, the 28. of the 8. moneth of Auguſt 1611. for perſiſting in
theſe ſinnes following.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 For leauing the Church.</item>
                              <item> 2 For ioyning with thoſe whome wee haue
excommunicated, as <hi>Chriſtopher Lawne</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                              <item> 3 For contentious carriage in refuſing to
ſpeake to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders when he came vnto them, otherwiſe than by writing
which he brought, and would haue them alſo to anſwer him in writing
againe.</item>
                              <item> 4 He despiſed the voice of the Church,
refuſing to come in publique at their ſending for him.</item>
                              <item> 5 And while he ſtood a member of vs, he
refuſed to partake in the Lords Supper.</item>
                           </list>
                           <closer>
                              <signed> 
                                 <list>
                                    <item>Daniel Studley.</item>
                                    <item>Edward Benet.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Hauing anſwered vnto the Copie of <hi>Chr. Lawne</hi> his
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, we deſire it may be conſidered, that therein alſo we
haue giuen anſwer touching the reſt of the men and women that were
excommunicate at the ſame time; there being no particular ſinne named and
obiected vnto anie of them in the copies of their Excommunications, which was
not contained in <hi>Christopher Lawnes,</hi> and therein anſwered alſo.
And for thoſe that were a month after excommunicate <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22763:11"/> with
<hi>Iohn Fowler</hi> for giuing teſtimonie vnto our cauſe, in anſwering
this copie of his excommunication we do herein alſo giue anſwer for them:
there being nothing further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt any of them, than is here
obiected vnto him. To come then vnto the anſwer hereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Firſt they condemne him <hi>for leauing the
Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is no ſinne to leaue that Church, that leaueth all other
Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ioyning with thoſe whom we haue excommunicate; as Chr.
Lawne, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>1</label> Had <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> the
Father beene aliue at this time, and had teſtified as <hi>Chr. La. Cl.
Sa.</hi> againſt their ſchiſme, adding this vnto the reſt of his
ſuppoſed iniquities, we would not haue feared to ioyne with that
Excommunicate, while hee in like manner would haue embraced the Communion of a
true Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>2</label> Theſe <hi>Franciſcanes</hi>
themſelues are one Bodie, with an Excommunicate of Maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> companie: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they can iuſtly anſwere for
themſelues, in ioyning with ſuch an Excommunicate, the ſame may we
alſo, and much more.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>3</label> Againe, others of the
<hi>Brownists</hi> themſelues doe ſee the vanitie of the Excommunications
executed by <hi>Fra. Iohnſon, Dan. Stud. Ed. Benet &amp;c.</hi> and doe
receiue their Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates, as appeares in the practiſe of M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his companie. Are they ridiculous among themſelues,
and ſhall they be regarded of others?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For contentious carriage in refuſing to speake vnto the
El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22763:12"/>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>1</label> If they had beene Gouernours of a
true Church, and not of a Schiſmaticall Societie, then might they haue had
ſome reaſon to haue required his anſwere, as they here complaine for want
thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>2</label> Their manner to peruert mens
ſpeeches, and to catch at wordes, makes that it is not a ſafe thing for any
priuate man alone to ſpeake with their Elders. M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> that
ſought to 
<note n="*" place="margin">See the letter of <hi>Iohn Iohnſon,
art.</hi> 3.</note>enſnare his own Father, and to peruert his words, whom
will he ſpare? Now writing might haue preuented this danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He despiſed the voice of the Church &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>1</label> He ſaw ſo much deſpight and
iniurie ſhewed vnto others in the middeſt of that Church, that he had
iuſt cauſe to auoid the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">answer </seg>2</label> The voice of that Church is not
the voice of Chriſt, but the voice of Schiſme, Contention, Confuſion,
Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Error, and therefore is not to bee hearkened vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And while he ſtood a member of vs, he refuſed to partake
in the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the Reader know, that this refuſall of participating in
the Lords Supper with them, was vpon the point of leauing them, when he called
their Schiſme into queſtion, and began to doubt of his eſtate among them.
In this caſe he could not (of Faith) come to the Table of the Lord with
them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22763:12"/>
            <head>SECT. 2.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Containing a true relation of the Schiſme,
Diſſenſions, Blaſphemies, Hereſies, and horrible Crimes practiſed
by the Brownists or Separators.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertaine Articles againſt <hi>Dan. Studley,</hi> giuen to
M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> in their publike Congregation before their Elders, to
deſire his depoſition from his office, of being an Elder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>1</label> Firſt, for his
filthineſſe vſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his wiues daughter, with that moſt vngodly
allegation of Scripture for the defence thereof. This particular is of old
knowne vnto their Elderſhip, and modeſtie forbids vs to ſet downe the
manner of it, it is ſo impudent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>2</label> Secondly, for writing a moſt
vngodly letter, containing in it many vile and vngodly ſpeeches, not meet to
proceed out of any Chriſtians mouth, much leſſe to be written by an Elder
of the Church of Chriſt, in as much as writing is more adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp;
deliberate than ſpeech: alſo, this letter being ſo long, that it is
ſuppoſed it coſt him more than a moneths worke to copie and recopie the
ſame, being aboue 300 long lines cloſe ruled; ſome of this letter being
in moſt abhominable verſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>3</label> Thirdly, for teaching many
wicked and vngodly ſongs and rimes vnto children when he kept ſchoole; in
ſtead of cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing them, and learning them to know God, hee taught them
vaine, idle, and wicked ſongs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>4</label> Fourthly, for diſcloſing
the counſaile of the Elderſhip to <hi>Marie May</hi> in ſome particulars,
as wee can plainely proue in due time and place. This was a principall thing
alledged to depoſe M. <hi>de Cluſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>5</label> Fifthly, for his many
laſciuious attempts to a young maid <pb n="16" facs="tcp:22763:13"/> now of late, with
his beaſtly behauior to entice her to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his owne luſt, vnmeet to
be named.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the ſecond and to the fift, Edward Tolwine, Iohn
Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Ellen Vpton, Henrie Homline ſubſcribed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>6</label> Sixtly, there were brought
ſixteene articles againſt him, to proue the tenor and courſe of his life
to be partiall; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of two were proued, and acknowledged by him, and the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of ſixteene were alſo confeſſed in generall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>7</label> Seuenthly alſo, at the
ſame time it was proued, that hee tooke part with <hi>Iudith Holder</hi> in
knowne euill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>8</label> Eightly, for counſailing
<hi>Marie May</hi> to lye with her husband before they were married.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A conſideration of the common defences and excuſes made
for the reſtraining of Dan. Studley in his office.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">charge </seg>1</label> FIrſt it is pleaded often by
M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> That the offences committed by <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> are
his perſonall ſinnes, and not the ſinnes of his adminiſtration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereunto we anſwere; firſt, That ſuppoſe his offences
were onely perſonall ſinnes, yet might they be a iuſt cauſe of
depoſition. <hi>Abiathars</hi> ſinne and <hi>Reubens</hi> ſinne were
their perſonall ſinnes: Likewiſe Adulterie, Inceſt, Murder, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
Drunkenneſſe, Periurie, and Blaſphemie, are perſonall ſinnes, and yet
iuſt cauſes of depoſition; and therefore wee hold it a great error in M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> ſo to plead for him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the ſinnes of <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> are not onely
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſinnes, but alſo the ſinnes of his adminiſtration; as
namely, his partialitie in peruerting iuſtice and iudgement, his fauouring of
the guiltie, and his oppreſſing of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and his taking of bribes
to this end; as namely, ioynts of meat and bottles of wine from Miſtreſſe
<hi>M.M.</hi> as hath been confeſſed by her ſelfe: without which gifts
(as ſhe ſaith) ſhe had not continued ſo long in the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22763:13"/>Againe it is pleaded for him, <hi>That he
hath acknowledged his offence, and that he hath repented for the
ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereunto we anſwere; firſt: That ſuppoſe he had truely
repented; yet is not his repentance ſufficient to retaine him in office. An
adulterer, traytor, murtherer, may, through Gods mercie, truly repent; and yet
ſuch ought to be depoſed from their office.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the repentance of <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> is not to be
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, becauſe hee ſtill ſeekes to excuſe and diminiſh his
faults; as namely, by pleading for himſelfe touching maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> daughter, that he knowes not whether ſhe be male or
female. For, if this were ſo, as he ſaith (though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the contrarie is
affirmed and teſtified againſt him) yet is it a praiſe of the maid who
reſiſted his leaud attempts; and not his praiſe. Who doubts but that he
would haue knowne whether ſhee had been man or woman, if ſhee would haue
yeelded to his luſt? This and ſuch like excuſes are no tokens of heartie
repentance.</p>
                  <p>Further, it is often obiected vnto vs by maſter
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> That by our dealing againſt <hi>Dan. Studley We do (with
Cham) vncouer the nakedneſſe of our Father, and therefore are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of
the Curſe</hi> that was laid vpon him by <hi>Noah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, we anſwere, It is not we, but <hi>Dan. Studley</hi>
himſelfe, that hath in ſhamefull and horrible manner vncouered the
nakedneſſe of his owne fleſh; not as <hi>Noah</hi> that once ſlipped,
and was in his ſleepe vncouered ignorantly and againſt his will,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 9.24. but ſundrie times, being awake, wittingly and purpoſely
vncouered himſelfe, and ſhewed his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and this vnto the eyes
of a maid: euen as the Serpent, that ſhewed the forbidden fruit vnto the
woman. To what good end could this be?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as he hath vncouered his owne nakedneſſe: ſo
hath he alſo violently vncouered the nakedneſſe of others, of diuers
maids; being ſuch a ſeruant of Sinne and ſtrange Luſt, 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22763:14"/> he is liker vnto <hi>Cham,</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi>
whoſe curſe was to be a ſeruant of ſeruants. Is not his noſe and
eares to bee cut for theſe things?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. The testimonie of father <hi>Tolwine</hi> with vs
against their iniustice, ſchiſme, and ſlander.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His old man (Father <hi>Tolwine</hi>) being about foureſcore
yeares of age, the ancienteſt of their company, who ſaw the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the ſeparation, hauing oft, of old, entertained maſter <hi>Browne</hi>
into his houſe, where many conſultations were held a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter,
before the reſolution of renouncing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of England was
agreed vpon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore maſter <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> or any of the
<hi>Franciſcans,</hi> did dreame of this way, vpon the firſt ſeparation
of <hi>Browne,</hi> was much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to follow him in this ſchiſme; and when
<hi>Browne</hi> went to dwell at Middleborough, reſolued to haue gone after
him him thither; and to that end ſold vp his liuing: but by the prouidence of
God, before he was paid for the ſame, the man that bought it died ſuddenly,
and ſo that bargaine came to nothing. And before he could againe take order
for his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he vnderſtood of the great troubles among them of the
ſeparation at Middleborough; the diſſolution of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pony; the
departure of <hi>Browne</hi> from that place; and in fine, the departure of
<hi>Browne</hi> from his profeſſion alſo. But after this againe, the
doctrine of <hi>Browne</hi> being taken vp and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by <hi>H. Barrow,</hi>
and afterwards by <hi>Francis Iohnſon,</hi> the mind of this old man was
againe troubled by their books and writings; in ſo much that at length, after
he had been long toſſed vp and downe with the winde of their deceitfull
doctrine, he left his old wife and friends, and came vnto Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam, there
to remaine with the <hi>Brownists,</hi> about ſome <pb n="19" facs="tcp:22763:14"/> fiue
or ſixe yeeres agone. And during this time of his abode among them, he walked
vnblameably amongſt them; hee was generally honored of them all, and
reſpected aboue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others. But now at laſt ſeeing the hatefull
contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; ſeeing their ſchiſme to rend it ſelfe in
peeces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many other ſchiſmes; ſeeing <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> to be
maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his wickednes againſt ſo manifold and pregnant
teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of thoſe that ſought his depoſition; ſeeing thoſe that
witneſſed againſt their corruptions to be either diſcouraged and faint
on the one ſide, or to be reiected and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated on the otherſide: it
pleaſed God hereby to enlarge his heart to vnderſtand the truth, and after
long and ſerious conſideration to ſee the error of his ſchiſme, and
to forſake the ſame. While he was thus pricked in his heart, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed
about his eſtate, he came vnto ſome of vs whom they had excommunicated; he
came vnto vs with teares, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and wringing his hands, ſcarce able to
ſpeake for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; and when he had recouered himſelfe he cried out vnto
vs, <hi>What ſhall I do? I ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the wicked are
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and vpholden in their wickedneſſe; I ſee that the innocent
are oppreſſed in their innocencie; I ſee that the communion of the godly
is reiected; and thoſe that are moſt vngodly, are they that ſeparate
themſelues from thoſe which bring forth better fruits of faith and
repentance.</hi> When it was vnderſtood among them, that Father
<hi>Tolwine</hi> was troubled about their dealings, their Elders ſent for
him, to whom he came, and there alſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed his diſlike of their
courſes. After this, Father <hi>Tolwine</hi> withdrew himſelfe from their
ſchiſmaticall Aſſemblies, and left his ſeparation which had ſo long
time kept him in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; and ſince that time hath profeſſed that his
comfort and peace is now as great, as his griefe and perplexitie was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
yea often ſince hath he melted in teares of comfort and ioy, for that it hath
pleaſed the Lord to deliuer him from ſo great a thraldome.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we deſire maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> to remember
the cauſe of <hi>Geffrey Whittakers and Iudith Holder.</hi> Theſe being
found <pb n="20" facs="tcp:22763:15"/> in bed together, and the action being naughtie, yet
<hi>Geffrey Whittakers</hi> excuſed the matter, that he did it not to
ſatisfie his luſt, but to comfort <hi>Iud. Holder;</hi> being ſicke to
keepe her warme; and with diuers words to that purpoſe, as though he had
ſought to performe a dutie of Chriſtian loue; and not an action of wanton
luſt. <hi>Geffrey Whittakers</hi> in theſe vile excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was by ſome
maintained: <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> in ſpeciall manner ſeeking to cleare him,
and to excuſe the matter. But how did it go in the end? was not their
wickedneſſe found out at laſt? was not <hi>Geffrey Whittakers</hi> at
length brought to confeſſe his filthineſſe, through the purſuit of
ſome of them which are now in maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> company? As
<hi>Dan. Studley</hi> ſtroue long in vaine for <hi>Geffrey Whittakers:</hi>
ſo let maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> thinke he ſtriues in vaine for <hi>Dan.
Studley,</hi> whoſe leaud luſt appeares by his leaud attempt, as well as
the others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. The copie of <hi>Robert Bulwards</hi>
ſuſpenſion and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication: with an anſwere thereunto.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="excommunication">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>
                                    <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Obert Bulward</hi> was ſecluded from the
publique meetings of the Church. December 1. 1611. For contentious and
troubleſome dealing when the Church was met together for miniſtration of
the Word and Sacraments, partaking with 
<note n="*" place="margin">Natth San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note>another,
that was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debarred the Churches meetings for communicating with railers and
excommunicate perſons, and going about to defend his ſo doing: it being
then alſo ſignified vnto him, againe &amp; againe, by ſome of the Elders,
that if he did not reſt, we would conſider what to do with him
likewiſe.</p>
                              <p>The thirtieth of Ianuary 1612. <hi>Robert Bulward</hi>
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid was cut off from the Church. 
<list>
                                    <item>
                                       <label type="milestone">
                                          <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>1</label> FOr
communicating with railers and excommunicates, and leauing the ſinceritie of
Truth, wherein he was before; and <pb n="21" facs="tcp:22763:15"/> withſtanding our
publique teſtimonie concerning ſeparation from the Apoſtaſie and
corruptions of Antichriſt, and ſuch as main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, with oppoſition
againſt the truth of Chriſt.</item>
                                    <item> 
                                       <label type="milestone">
                                          <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>2</label> For
ſlandering maſter <hi>Studley</hi> in ſome things which he could not
proue againſt him.</item>
                                    <item> 
                                       <label type="milestone">
                                          <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>3</label> For
deſpiſing the Gouernours of the Church.</item>
                                    <item> 
                                       <label type="milestone">
                                          <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>4</label> For
diſorderly and ſeditious walking among the brethren.</item>
                                    <item> 
                                       <label type="milestone">
                                          <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>5</label> For refuſing
to come when hee was laſt ſent for to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>All theſe are anſwered, as in the former
Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The teſtimonie of the Dutch Church concerning the
Browniſts.</head>
                  <p>WHen as they ſent their meſſengers with ſome
queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto the Dutch Elderſhip, they receiued this anſwere from
them, That <hi>they did not acknowledge their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie to be an
Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblie, or a lawfull Church.</hi> And when maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and others of them were inſtant to heare reaſons of this
anſwere from them; it was further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, They would do it if they ſaw
it needfull, or <hi>if they found any thing that was worthie of
anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The teſtimonie of the Magiſtracie of Amſterdam
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Browniſts.</head>
                  <p>THe Magiſtrates both of old, againſt maſter
<hi>White,</hi> and now of late in ſuit about their meeting-houſe; when
they ſought to lay in their action in the name of the Church, they were
repelled by the Magiſtrates that are members of the Dutch Church; they would
not receiue complaint from them in the qualitie or name of a Church, or the
name of any Elder or Deacon, but as from priuate men; The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates told
them that they held them <hi>not as a Church, but as a Sect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22763:16"/>
                  <head>M. Iohnſon his vnnaturall dealing with his
brother.</head>
                  <p>WE 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>G. Iohnſon</hi> his
diſcourſe of troubles and excom. <hi>p.</hi> 36. 37</note>read, that his
brother <hi>George</hi> being in extreame want, liuing vpon bread and water
onely, Maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> did then hide his face from his poore
brother, and ſhut vp the bowels of compaſſion againſt him, whileſt
others inſulted againſt the afflicted, and bad him ſell his Bookes, his
Couerlet, and his Cloke alſo, as others witneſſe. Doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
breake the bond of nature, and diſſolue the duties of kindred and
brotherhood?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. More of the wickedneſſe of Studley,
tranſlated out of the Dutch.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Engliſh Reader be not altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from the
knowledge of the Dutch ſtorie, concerning the notable exploits of this famous
Franciſcan, <hi>D. Studley,</hi> let him know, that herein is deſcribed, 1.
his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable wreſtling with his wiues daughter, his breathleſneſſe,
his bluſhing, his abaſhment, his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters colour. 2. M. <hi>Hintons</hi>
trouble for the conſtruction of it. 3. The penſiueneſſe, weeping, and
crying of <hi>Studleyes</hi> wife. 4. <hi>Studley</hi> his riſing out of his
bed, and going into his daughters ſlap-camer to kiſſe her, to ſhew,
that he loued his daughter for his wiues ſake. 5. His punching of his wife
with knees and elbowes, vpon her admonition and counſaile ſhe gaue him. 6.
The deuiſe betwixt Miſtreſſe <hi>Hinton</hi> and the Mother, to
chaſtiſe the daughter that had occaſioned her Mother ſo many beatings.
7. <hi>Studley</hi> his proceeding vnto further dalliance. 8. The blew eye that
<hi>Studley</hi> gaue his <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22763:16"/> wife. 9. His reſpect of the
daughter aboue the Mother. 10. The repentance that <hi>Studley</hi> his wife
was brought to for complaining vnto one that was not of their Church, and the
many ſtripes that ſhe receiued for the ſame. 11. The feare of
<hi>Studley</hi> his wife. 12. The knowledge that others had of his dealing.
13. His mocking of his wife.</p>
               <p>Thoſe perſons which are figured out vnto vs by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
creatures, vnfit to be ſacrificed, to be eaten, or to be touched, may not be
retained in office in the Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe that by office beare the
veſſels of the Lord, ought to be cleane, <hi>Eſay</hi> 52.11. whereas on
the contrarie, thoſe perſons are a meanes to defile and pollute euery
veſſell that they touch, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 11.32.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But <hi>Daniel Studley</hi> is ſuch a
perſon as is figured out by thoſe vncleane creatures of all ſorts. 
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note>For to ſpeake of
the foure-footed beaſts, and firſt of them which chew the Cud, and doe not
diuide the Hoofe, he is like vnto the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell, in reſpect of the great
vncleanneſſe aboue noted: and therefore to retaine this Camell in the
dignitie of an office, euen then alſo when thoſe which did but heare the
Word of God preached in other true Churches, are not retained in Communion;
What is it elſe, but with thoſe partiall and blind guides to ſtraine out
a Gnat, and ſwallow a Camell? <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.</note>Againe, of thoſe
beaſts which diuide the Hoofe, but chew not the Cud, he is like the filthie
Swine; for that although by his repentance he ſeemed to be waſhed from his
former vncleanneſſe, he hath yet now of late, like the Swine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to
wallow himſelfe in the ſame mire of vncleanneſſe with other maides,
according to the true Prouerbe, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</note>For vncleane creatures in the waters hauing not
ſinnes and ſcales: firſt hee is like vnto the ſlipperie Eele without
ſcales: for what wickedneſſe is there which by his ſlipperie ſhifts
and windings he knowes not how to excuſe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? Is it not a common
ſaying among them, If I had <hi>Dan. <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22763:17"/> Studley</hi> on my
ſide, I care not what matter any ſhould haue againſt me?</p>
               <p>Againe, for the creatures in the waters without ſinnes, he is
like vnto the hard ſhell-fiſh, being as bold and ſtout to maintaine his
deuiſe, as he is ſubtill and politike in deuiſing the ſame. For when as
in the middeſt of all his iniquitie he ſtandeth vp in the Publike to
diſcourage thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained on him, profeſſing that if any minded
him, he would alſo mind them: Is not this an hard ſhell of impudencie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.14.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>Touching the vncleane among the Fowles; firſt there
are ſpecially noted all kind of rauening birds: as the Eagle, the Griffon,
the Vulture, and Kite, after his kinde, and all Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens after their kinde. Now
for clawes to ſcratch and gripe withall, how notable is <hi>Dan. Studley</hi>
in his letter to <hi>Sam. Fuller?</hi> How full of ſcratching and bitter
rayling is it? And for his adminiſtration at home, there was neuer any poore
bird that did moue the wing, open the mouth, whiſper or chirpe againſt him,
but this partiall Griffon hath ſet the print of his clawes vpon him. As
<hi>Aſhur</hi> boaſteth of himſelfe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 10.14. ſo, in
effect, haue they boaſted ouer them that riſe vp to complaine of
<hi>Studley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, among the vncleane birds the Night-fowles are often
noted; as namely, the Night-crow, the little Owle, the Back or Bat. And theſe
alſo doe repreſent vnto vs the ſcandalous walking of <hi>Dan.
Studley,</hi> ſo often and ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily haunting with other mens wiues,
at vnſeaſonable times of the night, as namely with Miſtreſſe <hi>M.
V. C. K. D.</hi> and diuers others heretofore. And yet this Night-crow being
admoniſhed of the great appearance of euill herein, hath refuſed to hearken
thereunto, or to amend his euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29.30.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> As for the creeping things among them; the Mouſe, the
Rat, the Lizard, the Moule, that lurke in holes, and hide themſelues in the
duſt, are noted for vncleane creatures: and theſe doe verie fitly
repreſent the lurking nature of <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22763:17"/> 
                  <hi>Dan. Studley,</hi>
that can ſo cunningly hide himſelfe in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. But eſpecially,
among the creeping things, the Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, that is ſo famous for changing it
ſelfe into (almoſt) all colours, is moſt fit to repreſent vnto vs an
hypocrite, ſuch an one as <hi>Daniel Studley,</hi> whoſe vſe is to paint
ouer the fouleſt faces with the faireſt colours of Holineſſe, Religion,
and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For example, <hi>Iudith Holder</hi> being accuſed for
vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and vnnaturall dealing towards her husband, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſicke
of the Plague, and being (as he thought) readie to giue vp the ghoſt, hauing
ſuch grieuous pangs of death vpon him, ſhe then neglected him, yea ſhamed
not then to ſit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his head and ſing. But here <hi>Dan. Studley</hi>
caſteth his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour vpon it, and ſayth, That it might be a moſt holy and
religious action to praiſe the Lord with ſongs in aduerſitie. Againe,
<hi>M. M.</hi> being ſhut out of the Church for ſinne, and to come in
againe, ſhee boaſted, That if ſhee were in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, all the Diuels in
Hell ſhould not get her out. This ſpeech being reproued by ſome of vs,
<hi>Dan. Studley</hi> in their Elderſhip caſt his colour vpon it, ſaying,
It ſeemed to be a very holy ſpeech, ſhewing her faith, and hope of
aſſiſtance from the Lord. Againe, when he was found hidden behind the
basket at <hi>Iud. Holders</hi> houſe, hee made this holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, That he
hid himſelfe to ſee the behauior of <hi>G. P.</hi> who came thither after
him: ſo watchfull and vigilant an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer was he. Alſo, <hi>M. M.</hi>
hauing beene in a whore-houſe vpon ſome occaſion, and creeping thence out
at a window in a very vntoward manner, was excuſed by <hi>Dan. Studley,</hi>
who alledged in her defence the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> That by the
Diſciples was out a window, through the wall of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, let downe by a
rope in a basket, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.25. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.33. A number of
ſuch inſtances might be brought to ſhew the colourable dealing of this
hypocriticall Camelion. And therefore, ſithence ſuch vncleanneſſe of
all ſorts is found in him, we are fully perſuaded, that he is vnworthie to
beare office and dignitie, that beares ſo much reproach, and ſo iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
for his ſinne. Further, rayſing ſedition among themſelues, 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22763:18"/> the queſtion is, Whether M. <hi>Amſworth</hi> haue
carried away the Church with him, or whether M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> keepe the
Church ſtill with him? And as they haue an Eccleſiaſticall ſuit about
the kernell, which of them ſhould be the people of God and the true Church,
ſo haue they another ciuile contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſhell and the huske, who
ſhall haue the meeting-houſe where this Church ſhould meete together. In
the meane time the two houſes, where the ſeuerall factions of theſe two
ſeditious Captaines doe meet, being in the ſame ſtreet, and within one
houſe of another, are much like vnto thoſe two Wells <hi>Eſeck</hi> and
<hi>Sitnah</hi> (Sedition and Diſſenſion) or ſtrife and hatred.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.20.21.</note> But bleſſed be God, who hath
deliuered vs both from M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> Apoſtaticall <hi>Eſeck,</hi>
and from M. <hi>Amſworths</hi> ſchiſmaticall <hi>Sitnah;</hi> and not
onely ſo, but hath alſo brought vs vnto <hi>Rehoboth,</hi> or
Largeneſſe, by enlarging our hearts to embrace the Communion of thoſe
true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, from which the partition-wall of their ſeparation had
excluded vs and ſhut vs out before.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi>
12.</note> Wee pray the Lord for them alſo, that they may be likewiſe
enlarged, that the chaine of their Schiſme, which keepes them ſo ſtrait,
may be broken, and they at length be brought to entertaine Communion with the
people of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Vnder the hand of the Secretarie and Seale of the
Citie in this forme as followeth.</head>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="extract">
                           <head>Extracted out of a certaine Booke of M. Whites,
intituled</head>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                                 <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Briefe diſcouerie of ſome
of the abhominations daily practiſed and encreaſed amongst the Engliſh
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of the Separation, remaining for the preſent at Amſterdam in
Holland. <hi>Fol. 1.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That they abound (aboue others)
with all kind of debate, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:22763:18"/> malice, adulteries, couſenages,
and ſuch other like enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Fol. 1.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Daniel Studley, an Elder of their
Church, a man (not onely for his filthineſſe with his wiues daughter, but
alſo for ſupporting of manifeſt and ſhamefull vncleanneſſe and
couſening among them in 
<note n="*" place="margin">Namely <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Holder</hi>
and others.</note>others) fitter for the Stewes, than to be an Elder in any
Chriſtian Societie. <hi>Fol. 7.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Yet would their Elder Dan. Studley
neuer ſo much as denie the matter of Inceſt with his wiues daughter.
<hi>Fol. 17.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But their Deacon Chriſtopher
Bowman, for his deceiuing of many poore, euen of their owne companie, of halfe
that which the Magiſtrats of Narden had giuen them weekely, was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,
when it came to light through widow Colgates meanes, called Iudas the
Purſe-bearer in Narden, for ſo doing: not to speake of many ſuch like
inſtances that by him may be giuen. <hi>Fol. 15.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Haue they not abuſed the world,
that publiſh in print, that they neither receiue nor retaine any ſuch as
care not how they borrow, and make no conſcience to pay againe? I doubt not
but their owne hearts know how falſe this is in Iohn Nicholas, and others.
<hi>Fol. 13.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>They retaine amongst them open offenders, Iudith
Holder, Canadine, Iacob Iohnſon. <hi>Fol. 9. &amp; 10.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="extract">
                           <head>Extracted out of a certaine letter vnderwritten by M.
White the 20. of Iulie.</head>
                           <p>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I Deſire of God to keepe all his
people from ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, where Adulteries, Couſenages, and Thefts
are in ſuch abundance, as in the 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                                 <hi>viz</hi> the
Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</note>Engliſh Congregation of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam, that I ſpeake not
of br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>kerage of whores, and other
filthineſſe, too too bad.</p>
                           <p>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This is true; There is no Sect in
Amſterdam (though manie) in ſuch contempt for filthie life, as the 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                                 <hi>viz.</hi> the
Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</note>Engliſh are.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:22763:19"/>Concerning theſe articles which they laied
in againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>White,</hi> as though he had ſlandered them
therein: when as maſter <hi>White</hi> had once taken order by his Atturny to
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the matter; whenas alſo hee had for proofe thereof brought
ſundry witneſſes before the Burgo-maſters; which there did teſtifie,
and by their oaths and depſitions confirme the things which maſter
<hi>White</hi> had written; then was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>White</hi> diſcharged, and
had libertie from the magiſtrates to goe for England, as his occaſions or
buſineſſe ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. And beſide their ſpeeches vnto him to
this purpoſe, this is manifeſt alſo by this authentique copy of the
ſentence pronounced in this caſe by the magiſtrates; as followes.</p>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="sentence">
                           <div type="original">
                              <head>Extract uyt t' Arrest-Rolle der Stadt
Amſtetredam.</head>
                              <p>SChepeuen geuen de fante tegens Francoys Ianſon,
ende Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drick Anſwert, ende doen voort profijt van dyen, aff t' ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt op
des oppoſants parſon gedaen ende condemneren de verſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chleuen
arreſtaiten inde coſten dezer instantie. Actum de 24. Febr. xvi. C. ſes.
preſentibus vt in Registro.</p>
                              <p>Thomas Weyts. contra</p>
                              <p>Francoys Ianſon, Iacob Ianſon, Hendrick Anſwert,
Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coys Blackwall, Daniel Studley, Christoſell Boman, Ian Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, Iudick
Holder, Willem Barbons, ende Thomas Biſchop.</p>
                              <p>Coll. M. Bouwer.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="translation">
                              <head>Extracted out of the Arrest Rolle of the Cittie of
Amsterdam.</head>
                              <p>THe Iudges giue default for not appearing against
<hi>Francis Iohnſon</hi> and <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> and in regarde
thereof diſcharge the Oppoſant of the Arrest done on his perſon,
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Arresters in costs and charges of this ſuite vnto this
preſent time. Actum the 24. of February 1606.</p>
                              <p>Thomas White against</p>
                              <p>Francis Iohnſon, Iacob Iohnſon, Henrie
Ainſworth, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Blackwell, Daniel Studley, Chriſtopher Bowman, Iohn
Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22763:19"/> Iudith Holder, William Barbor, <hi>and</hi>
Thomas Biſhop.</p>
                              <p>Conferred. M. Bower.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>By this ſentence it may appeare, that maſter <hi>White</hi>
was not onely acquit from their Arreſt by the magiſtrates, but alſo, that
they themſelues beeing the Arreſters were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the coſt and
charges of this ſuite vnto that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time. After which time there was
neuer any other ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence giuen by the magiſtrates to reuerſe the ſame:
in ſo much, that at length the Browniſts themſelues (although
troubleſome and contentious in this as in other actions) were content to let
their ſuite fall, and ceaſed to proceede any further therein. And much
better it had beene for them neuer to haue begunne it, than with ſo much
ſhame, and ſo many rebukes to leaue it off.</p>
               <p>And as maſter <hi>White</hi> himſelfe was thus acquit, ſo
was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo miſtris <hi>White</hi> his wiſe, by authoritie of the
magiſtrates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit in this matter, as appeareth by this copy of the Sentence
giuen in reſpect of her.</p>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="sentence">
                           <div type="original">
                              <head>Extract uyt t' Arrest-Rolle der Stadt
Amstelredam.</head>
                              <p>SChepeuen doen aff t'arrest op de parſoon van des
oppoſants huiistorowe gedaen. Actum de 25. Februar. xvi. C. ſes.
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentibus vt in Registro.</p>
                              <p>Thomas Weyts als man ende voocht van Roſe Weyts.
contra Daniel Studley.</p>
                              <p>Coll. M. Bouwer.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="translation">
                              <head>Extracted out of the Arrest-Rolle of the citie of
Amsterdam.</head>
                              <p>THe Iudges releaſe the arreſt done on the perſon
of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſants wife. Actum the 25. of February 1606.</p>
                              <p>Thomas White as husband and head of Roſe White.</p>
                              <p>against Daniel Studley.</p>
                              <p>Conferred M. Bower.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:22763:20"/>Here marke their notable partialitie, in
calling before the magiſtrates ſuch as in their ſpeech doe mention their
adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and yet let thoſe alone that commit the adulteries, and neuer
call them before the magiſtrates, although the facts bee ſo manifeſt,
that maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> himſelfe in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to maſter
<hi>White</hi> could not denie the ſame; as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>William Holder,
Thomas Canadine, Robert Baylie, &amp;c.</hi> Had it not beene as iuſt and as
neceſſarie to haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led theſe malefactours before the magiſtrates,
as to haue called maſter <hi>White,</hi> who did but publiſh what they had
done? Is it a leſſe matter for a <hi>Browniſt</hi> to commit ſinne,
than for an other man to ſpeake of it? Or ſhall the leſſe ſinne be
called into iudgement, when the greater ſhall bee let alone? <hi>George
Iohnſon</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Diſc. p 30.</note> telleth vs how
often his brother <hi>Francis,</hi> and <hi>Daniel Studley</hi> wiſhed for
magiſtracie againſt him: why could they not as well haue ſought the
benefit of magiſtracie againſt <hi>William Holder, Thomas Canadine,
&amp;c.</hi> when they might haue got the ſame?</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe they had ſome colour in the former thing, yet
what hinders them that now they will not or dare not call <hi>Iohn de Cluſe,
Iohn Trappes,</hi> and <hi>Richard Mansfield,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the magiſtrates,
as well as maſter <hi>White?</hi> If maſter <hi>White</hi> made mention of
their adulteries and vncleanneſſe, ſo doe theſe teſtifie of their
<hi>probable murder, approued whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and wretched periurie,</hi> and haue
alſo prouoked them to go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before
the magiſtrates about theſe things. Are not theſe offences as great, if
not greater, than thoſe which maiſter <hi>White</hi> obiected vnto them?
What is the cauſe of this their partialitie? why doe they threaten extreamity
to vs, and yet vſe ſo much lenitie towards thoſe that fall ſo hard vpon
them?</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>vncleanneſſe of Iudith Holder</hi> here
obiected by maſter <hi>White,</hi> it is a thing as euident as may be. For
<hi>Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Whitakers</hi> hath ſince that time openly confeſſed in the
middeſt of their Congregation, that hee hath laine with hee night after
night; and this by his owne open confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="31" facs="tcp:22763:20"/> in ſo
beaſtly and abhominable manner, as wee are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to report. Other of her
vncleaneneſſes are alſo noted before. And in fine, ſhe is found to be
ſo vncleane, as by the generall conſent of the <hi>Brownists</hi> ſhe is
caſt out of their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Dan. Studley</hi> did labour it euen againe to defend
her, after M. <hi>White</hi> had in print rebuked him for it; and when the
greateſt part of their congregation conſented to caſt hir out as
vnſauorie ſalt, yet would not <hi>Daniel Studley</hi> conſent, but
complained thereof and mourned for her; and not he only, but M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> alſo ſought to cloake her vncleaneneſſe, and to
diminiſh her ſinne, and the ſhame of <hi>Geffrey VVhitakers</hi> her
bedfellow, and would not haue it to be adulterie, vſing his diſtinction of
lying with a woman, and in a woman &amp;c. inſomuch, that many of his
<hi>Brownists</hi> were aſhamed to heare him ſo to pleade for ſuch a
ſtrumpet. <hi>Abraham Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie</hi> did then alſo very ſtiffely oppoſe
himſelfe againſt Saint <hi>Francis</hi> at that time, and preuailed ſo
farre, by comparing the matter with that place, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.4. that it was
at length concluded, that <hi>Iudith</hi> alſo was found and <hi>taken in the
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act.</hi> And how could hee ſtand againſt his people for the
ſupport of <hi>Iudith</hi> in ſo plaine a caſe, except hee could haue
pulled out their eies?</p>
               <p>Wherefore, howſoeuer the ſeparation in ſhew is <hi>a white
Art,</hi> yet to them that duely conſider the ſame it may eaſily appeare
to be a very <hi>blacke Art.</hi> This blackneſſe firſt ſhews it
ſelfe in the blacke ſpots, wherewith the Separatiſts are of olde
ſtained. For ſome particular inſtance hereof reade the Booke of
<hi>George Iohnſon;</hi> and (beſide other places) conſider thoſe 
<note n="a" place="margin">Diſc. of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. pag. 180.</note>
thirteene offences, or blacke ſpottes which he noteth in his brother
<hi>Francis;</hi> ſee the 
<note n="b" place="margin">Diſc. of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com pag. 183.</note>
ſeauen ſpots noted in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ainſworth;</hi> ſee the 
<note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 183.</note> twelue blacke ſpots
found vppon <hi>Daniel Studley;</hi> conſider the 
<note n="d" place="margin">Pag 190.</note> two and twenty blacke
ſpots obſerued and reprooued in their Elderſhip ioyntly; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
theſe, marke the tenne blacke ſpottes of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in generall. 
<note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 196.</note> Secondly, as their
blackeneſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <pb n="32" facs="tcp:22763:21"/> is thus to be noted, ſo
in the next place obſerue their Art, which they haue to make others blacke by
ſlaundering and ſpeaking euill of their eſtate. This Art of ſlaunder
may well be called a blacke Art. Now for the euidence of their skill in this
Art, we referre the Reader to that generation of ſlanderers hereafter
diſcribed in this Treatiſe, where <hi>Barrow</hi> and his diſciples doe
ſo practiſe this blacke Art, that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> owne
words it may iuſtly bee ſaide vnto them. 
<note place="margin">Enquir. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>The very ſhame of
men, if no feare of God, might haue reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their lying lippes, and kept
them from blaſpheming the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with ſo blacke a mouth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. A compariſon betweene two notable Separatiſts,
<hi>Daniel Studley,</hi> a Franciſcane, and <hi>Richard Mansfield</hi> an
Ainſworthian.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The iniquitie of <hi>Richard Mansfield</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
notable.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 By his cruell tasking, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, &amp; exacting
the task impoſed; by ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging weights of lead vpon his maids arme while ſhe
ſpinned, as though otherwiſe the worke had bin too light and eaſie: and
the inflicting a cruell punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when the worke was not accompliſhed.
Though the Egyptian bondage was grieuous, yet amongeſt all 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22763:21"/> 
                     <hi>Pharaohs</hi> taske-maſters we reade of none called
<hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> nor yet of none ſo wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly cruell as he.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 By a ſhamefull and vile manner of whipping his 
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eli. Ap. and Do. Ha.</hi>
                     </note>
maids ſtarke naked, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eighteene years of age. All the particular
accidents therein are too vile to bee ſpoken.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 By his cruel nipping and pinching of his maids by the
armes, in ſo much that the skinne of 
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Do. Ha.</hi>
                     </note> one of them
firſt rent with whipping, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cruſhed with nipping, hath broken out
into ſoares, the filthy matter wherof hath come running downe to the wriſts
of her hands, as ſhee hath ſit at her wheele.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 By his moſt barbarous and beaſtly manner of
hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp his 
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Do Ha.</hi>
                     </note> maid by the
ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſtarke naked, firſt binding her <pb n="34" facs="tcp:22763:22"/> hands with
cords, tying them vp to ſome high place, then taking away the thing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſhe ſtood, and ſo letting her hang from the ground while hee ſpent
diuers rods vpon her: yea and after this whipping he let her ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo a great
while before he would take her downe. Alas for the daughters of the
ſeparation, is this the libertie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that account themſelues the only
free people? The virgins of <hi>Sion</hi> in the daies of their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie
found more fauour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Babylonians, then this <hi>D. Hanwell</hi> not
handled well among the <hi>Browniſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 By executing iudgement vpon his maid, ſometime
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſhew of any fault was committed: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by calling his
maid out of her bedde betimes in the morning, not ſuffering her to put on her
cloathes, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her further to ſtrip her ſelfe, making her alſo to
fetch out the rods, then telling her alſo that he knew ſhe would not
finiſh her taske by the weekes end, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was beſt to giue
her <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22763:22"/> correction before-hand, and ſo before the fault
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inflicted the puniſhment that might afterwards happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be
deſerued.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 By vſing ſuch rigour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his ſeruant in
exacting the taske of worke impoſed, that her worke being to ſpin
bombaſine wooll, ſhee hath often for feare been glad to eat vp the wooll,
which ſhee could not ſpin time enough, leſt ſome remnant of the wooll
being ſeen and found, it might therby appeare that her taske was not
finiſhed: and ſo ſhee her ſelfe to haue bin brought like a ſheep
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſhearer, before <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> the ſtripper, and ſo
not onely to haue had her wooll or woollen garments to bee ſtript off her
backe, but alſo to haue had her skin ſhorne with the ſharpe ſheares of
<hi>Mansfields</hi> cruell rods.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22763:23"/>7 By his barbarous and beaſtly
crueltie in compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his maid to eate her owne excrements: for when ſhe
had once for feare eaten her wooll, and the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine was from time to
time purged out of her bodie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, noted by
our Sauiour, 
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi>
15.17.</note>
                     <hi>Whatſoeuer entereth into the mouth goeth into the belly, and
is caſt out into the draught,</hi> yet this monſtrous wretch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to
the knowledge here of; did not only rake and take forth out of the draught that
which the Lord would haue to be 
<note n="e" place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.13.</note> couered:
but further in moſt abominable manner hee ſhamed not to take that dung, and
by violence to put it into her mouth, and with a crane of braſſe to
thruſt it downe her throat, in ſo much that the poore maid crying
miſerably out for water, was almoſt ſlockned before ſhee could get
redreſſe againſt the vexation of this loathſome tormentor, (hath the
like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer been read or heard of?) It was a grieuous viſion and a type of
great miſerie, when the Lord commanded <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> to prepare &amp;
bake <pb n="37" facs="tcp:22763:23"/> his bread 
<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 4
12.13.14.15.16.17</note> with <hi>the dung that commeth out of man,</hi> to
ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the <hi>aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> that ſhould enſue of the euils
threatened; and the Lord in mercie ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Prophet, and at his praier did
mitigate the thing; but behold in this <hi>R. M.</hi> a more grieuous ſight
or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a type of <hi>astoniſhment,</hi> not to prepare meate with
dung, but to eat that dung as meat, not by commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, but by the luſt of the
<hi>diuell:</hi> It was horrible in <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaketh</hi> a Pagan, to threaten
his enemies with the eating of their owne dung through famine; but it was more
hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, ſauage and vnhumane in <hi>Ric. Mansfield,</hi> a brother, euen a
brother of the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to vſe this crueltie, and with his own hands by
force to do it, not vnto an enemie, but vnto a ſiſter of the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
&amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22763:24"/>8 By making his maides immediately
after this whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and hard vſage to ſing ſongs of mirth in the
middeſt of their ſorrow and teares, contrarie to their feeling, and
contrarie to the order of the Apoſtle, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.13. And not onely
this, but alſo by moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in prophane manner at their ſinging; and for
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the diſtreſſed perſon beginning to ſing, 
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.</note>
                     <hi>O Lord
conſider my distreſſe, &amp;c.</hi> hee would then in deriſion ſpeak
vnto them, <hi>Oh you are in great diſtreſſe ſure &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 137.1.2.3.4.</note>As the
cruell ſcoffing Babylonians of old required ſongs and mirth of the Iewes in
their captiuitie, ſaying vnto them, <hi>Sing vs one of the ſongs of
Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> euen then when the Iewes ſate weeping by the riuers of Babell,
and had hanged vp their Harps vpon the Willowes: ſo this cruell ſcoffing
<hi>Browniſt</hi> did then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſongs and mirth of his captiue maides,
when they had hanged vp the Harpes of their mirth, and had rather to haue fit
weeping than ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; yea, and conſtrained the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſing ſo as the
Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians could not do the Iews.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22763:24"/>9 By alledging Scripture (after the
manner of the <hi>Browniſts</hi>) to defend &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the crueltie
which hee vſed towards his maides, as namely, <hi>That if a man ſmite his
ſeruant, or his maid, with a rod, and they die not vnder his hand, but
continue a day or two dayes, he ſhould not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, becauſe they are
his money.</hi> Exod. 21.20, 21. Whereas this Scripture can be no warrant for
his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie; both becauſe his maids were no bondſlaues vnto him, bought
with his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as alſo becauſe that law was in peculiar to the Iewes, and
euen then was a iudiciall Statute, and did not free the offendour from all
guilt of ſinne, but onely from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the ciuile
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:22763:25"/>10 By his carnall ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in
the middeſt of all his impietie; by his vſuall ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the time of
Gods worſhip: and this not onely when M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> preached, (for
then he plainely profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that hee did ſettle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſleepe,
accounting M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> a falſe Teacher, and vnworthie to be
hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto) but thus alſo hee ſlept, when M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi>
taught. And yet further, which is more ſtrange, hee did not onely ſleepe
whiles other preached and prayed, but euen when himſelfe hath beene praying
at home with his familie, his manner hath beene to fall aſleepe in the
middeſt of his prayer, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers then preſent haue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 By his notable hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in the middeſt of all
his iniquitie; and this not onely in his generall Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to
which (together with the reſt of his companions) hee ſayth vnto all the
reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world, <hi>Stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, I am purer and holier than
you:</hi> Nor yet onely by <pb n="41" facs="tcp:22763:25"/> ſeparating from other
<hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcan</hi> ſeparatiſts, and namely from <hi>Dan. Studley,</hi>
whom in ſpeciall manner hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, and ſayth vnto him, <hi>Stand
apart Studley, for I am holier than thou.</hi> But further, euen aboue many
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of M. <hi>Ainſworths</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, wherein he reſteth, he
pretendeth more puritie, is more ſmooth in his words, ſtricter in the
ſeparation, and makes greater ſhew of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pietie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:22763:21"/>
                  <head>The iniquitie of <hi>Daniel Studley</hi> appeares
notable.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 By his oppreſſion and preuenting of Iuſtice
tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole tenour of his adminiſtration, as hee himſelfe being
preſſed and proſecuted by ſome of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi>
people hath beene brought to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in generall. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and feare
of <hi>Studley</hi> haue bin heauier tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weights of lead vppon the fainting 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22763:21"/> armes of the poore people, that they durſt not deale
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Though the Phariſies laid heauy burthens vpon other mens
ſhoulders, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. yet among them al, we read of none called
<hi>Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> nor yet of any one whoſe manifold oppreſſions are ſo
often witneſſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 By a ſhamefull and vile manner of dealing with one
euen of the ſame maids, who comming out of the hands of <hi>Mansfield,</hi>
fell into the hands of <hi>Studley</hi> &amp; was ſaine to cry out of
<hi>Studley,</hi> as well as ſhee had done of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sfield</hi> before.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 By his cruel nipping and pinching euen of his owne
wife, as ſhe her ſelfe hath te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified vnto diuers, and is in part noted
before. Many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple talke of <hi>Fairies nippes,</hi> and of the blew arms
they make; but it is hard to ſay whether <hi>Fairies</hi> of the ſeparation
doe nip harder.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Studley</hi> indeed in this point dealt more
gently with the 
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eli. Ap.</hi>
                     </note> maid; whom
though he drew and haled violently at <pb n="34" facs="tcp:22763:22"/> the firſt, yet did
he not hang her vp ſo cruelly, but laid her and threw her vpon his bed in
more eaſie maner. And yet in matters of ſuite and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the
threeds of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill ſhifts hee doth as it were tye and bind the
ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, both men and women, which ſtand <hi>hanging in the cords of
doubt and feare,</hi> wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting long for an iſſue, and yet put off with
delayes. And yet not ſo, but that he himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath now long time
hung in feare, with the <hi>cord of de poſition,</hi> as it were about his
neck, waiting whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould be turned off from the ladder of his
dignitie.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 By executing iudgement vpon himſelfe before the
Iudges of the Congregation had pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced the ſentence of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation
againſt him. For as <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> that hanged
themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time, and as thoſe theeues that murther
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before the time to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the ſentence of the law, cannot be
defended therein; ſo <hi>Daniel Studley</hi> depoſing himſelfe, and
leauing his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice before ſentence, whether <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22763:22"/> of
deſpaire to keepe it, ſeeing the people ſo againſt him, or whether in
hypocriſie &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to moue the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to commiſeration, alwaies
his vntimely and vnorderly executing of himſelfe cannot bee iuſtified,
howſoeuer the cauſe of his condemnation might be ten times more iuſt then
the cauſe that <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> had againſt his maid.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 By vſing ſuch rigor to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his wife, in
threatning &amp; beating her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi>
3.19. in ſo much that by his cruelty, ſhe hath ſought, though not to eat
her wooll, yet to eate her word, by labouring that ſhee might not be called
to ſpeak thoſe things which ſhe knew of her husband, &amp; had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
told in ſecret; yea &amp; hath charged ſome to whom ſhee complained of
her miſeries, that they ſhould not vtter the ſame during her life, for
feare of his rage againſt her. And yet the greatnes of her miſery hath made
her to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her grief; &amp; the regard of her word would not ſuffer her to
deny the ſame, when ſhe was called to account for it.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22763:23"/>7 By his tyrannie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnto him
with other of the ſeparation, in drawing thoſe that had forſaken their
error to returne vnto their vomit againe, and to eate vp, though not the
excrements of their bodies, yet the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their error. It is moſt
ordinary with the <hi>Browniſts</hi> to charge thoſe that leaue their
ſchiſme and returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the true Churches <hi>to be as
dogs retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their vomit:</hi> as though the fellowſhip of the Saints,
in the holy things of God in other true Churches, were but as the vomit of
dogges, whereas indeed their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is but as the excrements and dung of
ſchiſmatikes; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which dung notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they are often drawne to
returne, and to eate vp the ſame. As for example, <hi>Edward Benet</hi>
hauing begun to purge out ſome of the excrements, firſt by entertaining
ciuill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of England, ſo farre as to marry a wife
from thence, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion by hearing maſter
<hi>Burges;</hi> when as after all he was brought againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22763:23"/> for theſe things: what did he elſe but returne to his
own excrements? Many ſuch examples might be alleaged, wherin as many among
them haue been vehement, ſo <hi>Dan. Studley,</hi> eſpecially in theſe
caſes hath bin moſt ſeuere, ſo that as in reſpect of his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies he
is generally noted for a <hi>Matchieuellian,</hi> ſo in reſpect of his
tyrannie for a <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filian,</hi> that with <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſeekes to
bring and enforce men vnto the eating of their owne dung.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 36.12.</note> Againe, as this is done indeed, ſo
in the accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the other Separatiſts, both of maſter
<hi>Ainſworthes</hi> and maſter <hi>Robinſons</hi> companie, the
<hi>Franciſcans</hi> being many wayes become notable <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtataes,</hi>
returning into errors about miniſterie and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from which they
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be purged, in reſpect of this apoſtaſie, they can be
accounted no better then dung-eaters, and dogges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to their vomit in
the eſtimation of other <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts:</hi> and thoſe which like
<hi>Fra. Iohnſon,</hi> and <hi>Dan. Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> do moſt vrge hereunto,
can be accounted no better then <hi>Manſuilians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22763:24"/>8 By teaching his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers (the
little children which learned of him) not the ſongs of Sion, not the
Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> (for that is an vſe that <hi>Studley</hi> hath
oft condemned) but filthie, vnſauorie, &amp; rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rimes, ſuch as wee are
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and loth to print or repeat the ſame, neyther meane wee to doe it,
vnleſſe wee bee further vrged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. The children in Maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> companie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
then he taught, haue not yet forgotten them. <hi>H. Barrow</hi> ſcoffing at
the Preachers in the Church of England, tels in his <hi>Diſcouerie,</hi> How
<hi>their mouth diſtilles, and their lippes drop downe ſuch old parables,
&amp;c.</hi> But much more iuſtly might it haue beene ſaid of
<hi>Studley,</hi> the auncient Elder, Prophet, and Preacher in the Church of
the <hi>Browniſts, that his mouth hath diſtilled, and his lippes dropped
downe ſuch old parables,</hi> as might farre better become the ſtreetes of
Sodome than of Sion, being indeede ſuch vncleane and ſtinking ſtuffe as
any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eares might iuſtly abhorre to heare their children
repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22763:24"/>9 By alledging Scripture in like
manner to iuſtifie his filthie behauior towards his wiues daughter: being
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued for his vncleane diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueries, not to be named, the prophane wretch
ſought to defend himſelfe by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Salomons</hi> ſearching
out of all ſecrets. Is there not here iuſt cauſe to exclaime a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt
him, as M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> in another place doth againſt M.
<hi>Iacob?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fran. Iohnſons</hi> anſwere to M.
<hi>Iac. p.</hi> 32.</note>
                     <hi>O ſhameleſſe mouth, O vnchriſtian
heart!</hi> Can any godleſſe Atheiſt abuſe the Scriptures more horribly
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this filthie <hi>Studley</hi> herein hath done? <hi>De Cluſe</hi> their
El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould haue bin depoſed for diſcouering the ſecrets of their
Conſiſtorie: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we would demand of M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> theſe
three queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: firſt, whether <hi>De Cluſe</hi> his vncouering of
ſecrets, or <hi>Studleyes</hi> ſearching out of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, be a greater
ſinne? ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, whether the ſecrets of their Conſiſtorie, or the
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of <hi>Studleyes</hi> priuat contemplation be greater ſecrets?
thirdly, whether it had not bin as iuſt to haue depoſed <hi>Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>
betimes, as to haue depoſed <hi>De Cluſe</hi> ſo haſtily. Further,
whether <hi>Studley</hi> for defending his filthineſſe, or
<hi>Mansfield</hi> for defending his crueltie, haue more horribly and wickedly
prophaned the name of God, wee leaue to be diſputed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the
<hi>Franciſcans</hi> and the <hi>Manſvilians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:22763:25"/>10 By the like ſecuritie in his
wicked courſe; his manner being alſo to ſleepe in time of publike
worſhip, though an Elder, and ſitting in a throne in a high and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
place, whereby his offence became more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and notorious. Theſe
circumſtances therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered on both ſides, it may bee
ſome queſtion, Whether of theſe two ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>Mansfield</hi> or
<hi>Studley,</hi> haue deſerued the more ſhame, and whether of them be the
more ſlouenly ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 By his notable hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in the middeſt of all
his iniquitie: He ſayth with <hi>Mansfield</hi> vnto all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Churches on earth, <hi>Stand apart, I am holier than you, I muſt touch no
vncleane thing; your worſhip is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, if I ſhould ioyne with
you.</hi> The like he now ſayth vnto the <hi>Manſvilian</hi>
Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:22763:25"/> and euen vnto <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>
himſelfe, whoſe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he much condemned, when as vpon ſpeciall
occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it was made knowne vnto him. And beſides this, euen aboue many of
the <hi>Franciſcane</hi> Separatiſts, his companions, he is ſmooth in
wordes, ſtrict in ſeparation, full of religious proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and can
cunningly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſinnes of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Saints to cloke his
impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, as though hee were as holy as the faithfulleſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God
vpon earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>Of theſe two, and ſundrie other ſuch like, there may
iuſtly be verified this Prouerbe, 
<q> 
                        <l>The ſtrictest in ſeparation,</l> 
                        <l>The leaudest in conuerſation.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. The teſtimonie of <hi>William Gilgate,</hi> one
of Maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> his companie, and that had bin a Miniſter in
England.</head>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="testimony">
                           <p>
                              <hi>
                                 <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord rebuke me not in thine anger, neither
cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe me in thy wrath, for thine arrowes haue light vpon me, and thine
hand lyeth vpon me. There is nothing ſound in my fleſh, becauſe of thine
anger; neither is there reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſinne,
&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Hauing now long time beene afflicted with ſharpe and 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22763:26"/> grieuous ſickneſſe, whereby it hath pleaſed God to
bring me vnto more ſerious and deepe conſideration of my eſtate, in
ſeparating from the Churches of Chriſt, and ſtill finding my ſeparation
to be more vnlawfull, the more I conſider the ſame: and while I felt my
ſelfe at the weakeſt and ſickeſt, and ſo preſſed with the force
of my diſeaſe, that I euen doubted of life, I felt my conſcience moſt
preſſed with deſire, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke my ſeparation; and therefore doe now
thinke it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, before I be taken away hence, and be found no more, or how
ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to diſpoſe of me by life or death, to
giue teſtimonie vnto the truth, whereof I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded in my ſoule.</p>
                           <p>And as mine owne diſeaſe, and the hand of God
ſtretched out vpon me, moueth me to conſider and teſtifie theſe things,
ſo the diſeaſe of the ſeparation, and the hand of God, which I ſee to
be ſtretched out againſt it, doth alſo draw me on the other ſide vnto
the ſame thing. The diſeaſe of the ſeparation is a hot and burning
diſeaſe, that conſumeth and deſtroyeth many with the poyſonous and
contagious heat thereof; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry companie among them is as a flame of
condemnation to deuoure another; the boyle of their contention ſwelleth and
burneth inceſtantly, and they haue yet no poulteſte to breake it, nor any
oyle to mollifie the ſame.</p>
                           <p>When as I firſt ſeparated from the Church of
England, and came to the Church of the Separation at Amſterdam, I had not
long continued therein, but that Church did rend in the middeſt, and
ſeparate one halfe from the other. There was I conſtrained to make a new
ſeparation again, and then I choſe rather to ſeparate from M.
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and to ioyne my ſelfe with M. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> who
ſtill kept their old rules, where by we were directly led to ſeparate from
M. <hi>Iohnſon.</hi> Being thus ſeparate againe, the contention grew ſo
extreame betwixt theſe two parts, that ſo many members on either ſide as
ſubmitted vnto the other, were by the reſt giuen to Sathan, and cut off by
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication. In this eſtate both of them boaſt againſt the other,
each ſide glorieth they haue killed the other, dach <pb n="43" facs="tcp:22763:26"/>
exalt themſelues, and each caſt downe and condemne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When two
harlots came before King <hi>Salomon,</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding earneſtly againſt one
another for the liuing childe, both laying clayme vnto it, <hi>Salomon</hi>
called for a ſword, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to diuide the liuing child, and to giue
the one halfe to the one, and the other halfe to the other. And vpon this
ſentence the King marking the compaſſion of the one to be kindled, and
ſeeing the other hardened and content to haue the child diuided, did thereby
find out the compaſſionat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whom he gaue the liuing child. But
theſe two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious women of the Separation, theſe two companies of M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and M. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> when they ſtriue for a member
going from one to another, haue not their compaſsion kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led toward their
children, like that tender and pitifull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that got her right before
<hi>Salomon,</hi> but both of them are hardened, both of them doe rather
chuſe to ſlay and diuide any of their children with the ſharpe ſword of
their excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, than that they ſhould lye in the boſome of the
others communion: What ſentence ſhould <hi>Salomon</hi> giue now in this
caſe? Surely, neither of theſe women are the right mothers of thoſe
children, whom they doe ſo diuide and hew aſunder; it appeares they neuer
trauailed in paine of them, they neuer begot them by their Miniſterie, but
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeduced and ſtolne theſe children from the ſides of other true
Churches, the right mothers, in whoſe wombes they were regenerate and borne
anew, they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hard-hearted and more cruell vnto them than
Oſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnto their young. What then remaineth to be done for the
changelings of the Separation? Let them open their eyes and looke about them;
let them learne to diſcerne their owne mother, from whom they were taken and
changed in their cradle; let them forſake their ſeparation, and ſucke the
milke of Schiſme no longer; let them returne to the communion of the
faithfull, both in England and in theſe reformed Churches, whom they haue
reiected as well as England.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="44" facs="tcp:22763:27"/>I was once halfe perſuaded, that
M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and M. <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> had beene thoſe two
witneſſes that ſhould propheſie in ſackcloth, <hi>Reu.</hi> 11.3.4.
&amp;c. but now finding that the fire which proceedeth out of their mouthes is
to deuoure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; finding that they vſe their power to ſhut heauen
one againſt another, eſteeming one another Apoſtataes &amp;
Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, one binding the ſinners which another looſeth, and binding
that which God doth not binde; finding that theſe two witneſſes doe not
agree in their teſtimonie, but beare witneſſe one againſt another,
laboring to reſtraine the raine and deaw from one another, and to turne the
waters of their ſeparation into bloud; ſeeing the ſpirit of the beaſt
is in them, to make warre, ouercome, and kill one another; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much alſo
as their corps doe lye as it were vnburied, and not in the ſtreets of Rome,
but in the ſtreet of the ſeparation; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo that the diſciples
of theſe two Prophets do reioyce and congratulate one another in their owne
vexation; and laſtly, ſeeing they haue thus layne, not three daies and a
halfe, but more than three hundred and a halfe, and yet no ſpirit of life
comes into them to ſet them on their feet againe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can I not
eſteeme them as thoſe two Oliue trees, and two Candleſtickes that ſtand
before the God of the earth. Yea, further I do deſire thoſe that yet follow
them, that they would, in the feare of God, be ſtirred vp by theſe
conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a little better to examine the grounds of their vnſound
ſeparation. As for my ſelfe, I doe now by this writing vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly
acknowledge my ſinne to be great, in renouncing the communion of ſo many
faithfull ſeruants of God, with whom I once liued in the Church of England; I
ſinned againſt God, and diſhonoured his name, in refuſing to heare the
word of Life preached in thoſe aſſemblies: the life, comfort, and
ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation that I expect and hope for in the kingdome of heauen is, by the
faith of the Goſpell preached in that Church, and preached there with more
power, fruit, and efficacie, than I euer yet heard in the Churches of the
ſeparation: the faithfull in that Church, whoſe fellowſhip in the
worſhip of God I <pb n="45" facs="tcp:22763:27"/> did once reiect, are thoſe with whom
I hope to reioyce in heauen, whom I do now alſo long after in the Lord. I
ſinned againſt them, in diſclayming their communion, and thereby haue
giuen euill example vnto many, and haue beene a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke vnto the
weake, whom I now deſire not to be offended nor ſcandalized by me.</p>
                           <p>I heare of late, that the Ladie C. a woman of great
eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (though liuing ſtill in England) hath yet deſired to be
receiued as a member of M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> Church: and it is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by
ſome of them, that in her ſickneſſe ſhe hath wiſhed to die as one
of them, and to end her dayes in that profeſſion: but for my part hauing
now had ſufficient experience of their wayes, I doe freely acknowledge and
profeſſe in this bed of my ſickneſſe (from which I know not whether
euer I ſhall ariſe vnto my former health) That it ſhou'd be my great
comfort to die in the communion of thoſe Churches whom they haue now
reiected, and to renounce my ſeparation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I be ſeparated out of this
world. And I doubt not, but if that ſeduced Ladie had in like manner with her
owne eyes ſeene the bitter fruits of this miſerable ſeparation, ſhe
would then account it her comfort to be free from ſuch a ſnare.</p>
                           <p n="1">1 There be at this preſent hanging ouer my head
two ſwords of Separation; the one is the ſword of the Lord, who by this
grieuous diſeaſe doth threaten to ſeparate my ſoule from my bodie, and
to bring me vnto the duſt of death: if this ſword fall vpon me, my hope is,
that it ſhal make way for me into heauen, into a glorious Communion with the
Lord, and innumerable Saints and Angels, Chriſt Ieſus being the Lambe of
God to take away my ſinnes, and being entred as a fore-runner within the
vaile to prepare a place for mee by the bloud of the euerlaſting
couenant.</p>
                           <p n="2">2 The other is the ſword of the Separatiſts,
whereby they threaten to excommunicate and cut me off, if I liue, and riſe
againe to come among them, and teſtifie againſt their Schiſme: If this
ſword fall vpon me, my hope is, that it ſhall make way for me into an
heauen vpon earth, into a gracious <pb n="46" facs="tcp:22763:28"/> communion with the
faithfull ſeruants of God in his viſible Churches, there to reioyce with
the ioy of Gods people: yea, whether they cut me off or not, my reſolution is
(if the Lord prolong my daies) to cut off my ſelfe from that their
ſchiſme, wherein I haue ſtood with them. And though I cannot but expect
much reproach and many hard ſentences (which they of the Separation will for
this cauſe paſſe vpon me) yet my hope is, that the Lord (which of his
mercie hath giuen mee leaue to ſee my error and his truth) will now alſo
ſtrengthen me by his grace to beare the euill ſpeeches which in this caſe
they vſe to poure out vpon thoſe that leaue them.</p>
                           <l>Surely I am readie to halt, and my ſorrow is euer
before me.</l>
                           <l>When I declare my paine, and am ſorrie for my
ſinne,</l>
                           <l>Then mine enemies are aliue and are mightie, and they
that hate me wrongfully are many.</l>
                           <l>They alſo that reward euill for good are mine
aduerſaries, becauſe I follow goodneſſe.</l>
                           <l>Forſake me not O Lord; be not thou farre from me my
God.</l>
                           <l>Haſt thee to helpe me, O my Lord, my ſaluation.</l>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>WILL. GILGATE.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>About a moneth or ſix weekes after this, when by the mercie of
God he was ſomething recouered of his ſickneſſe, he then by his
practiſe confirmed further that which he had written before, both by
embracing the communion of the Churches, which he refuſed before, in hearing
the Word, and praying with them &amp;c. As alſo by going vnto M.
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> Church, with which he had ioyned himſelfe before, and
there openly, in the middeſt of their Congregation, renounced his
fellowſhip with them, teſtifying, that they were in Schiſme: and for
further proofe hereof did afterwards giue vnto Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi>
diuers Arguments in writing, to proue them to be in manifold Schiſme, and
ſo finally left them quite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:22763:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Letters that paſſed betwixt M. <hi>Ames</hi>
and M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> touching the bitterneſſe of the
Separation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne point of Schiſme which M. <hi>Gilgate</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected vnto
M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> was, for their ſeparation in priuate from thoſe
particular perſons, which might be diſcerned to be true viſible
Chriſtians, euen by their owne confeſſion. This point, becauſe it is
further diſcuſſed in diuers Arguments and Writings betwixt Maſter
<hi>Ames</hi> and Maſter <hi>Robinſon,</hi> wee haue thought it meet to
publiſh them as they came vnto our hands, becauſe they ſerue much for the
declaration and manifeſtation of their Schiſme herein.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>G. M. and P.</head>
                     <p>SIr, I doe not deſire to multiplie many Letters, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> many words in this one Letter, I will paſſe by
therefore your cenſure. Your manner of ſeparation alſo I omit, whether it
be like or diſlike to that of the firſt reformed Churches, for you haue
yrons ynow in the fire about that queſtion: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I trouble you about
my aſſociates here, whom you deeme euill of, though they be vnknowne vnto
you: Onely that one point which containeth indeed the very bitterneſſe of
Separation, I would deſire you againe to conſider of, as you doe me;
<hi>viz. Whether there be not a viſible Communion euen out of a viſible
Church.</hi> Theſe reaſons ſeeme to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Whomſoeuer I can rightly diſcerne to haue
commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Ieſus Chriſt, with him may I haue viſible commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: the
reaſon is, becauſe that from viſible deſcrying of that inward
communion, doth neceſſarily follow externall <pb n="48" facs="tcp:22763:29"/>
communion. Neither can other ſufficient reaſon be giuen, why we ſhould
communicate with viſible Churches, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe wee viſibly
diſcerne, that they haue communion with Chriſt: Now <hi>quatenus ipſum
&amp; de omni conuertuntur.</hi> But we may diſcerne (euen by your
confeſsion) of ſome, out of a viſible Church, that they haue communion
with Chriſt. <hi>Ergo</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 That which is lawfull for them to doe which are no
members of a viſible Church, that is lawfull for others to ioyne with them
in: for that which is no ſinne in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, is none in the
acceſſorie, <hi>Cateris paribus.</hi> And it cannot be ſimply vnlawfull
to ioyne in any action that is lawfull, <hi>Quatenus talis;</hi> but it is
lawfull for Chriſtians conuerted, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen before they ioyne in any Church
(perhaps wanting knowledge of the true Conſtitution, perhaps oportunitie) to
worſhip God. Therefore</p>
                     <p n="3">3 It is neceſſarie, that before the couenant making
(which you hold to be the forme of a Church) they that are to make it, ſhould
ioyne together in prayer for direction, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and bleſſing,
yet they are not a Church vntill after: Therefore it is not only lawfull but
neceſſarie alſo, that there be a communion out of a viſible Church. You
may eaſily conceiue the forme and force of this Argument. If you anſwere
that they are a Church in deſire; that is to forſake your poſition: for
deſire to be, doth imply, that as yet they are not; <hi>A velle ad eſſe
non ſequitur ratio.</hi> I will not be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tedious vnto you. Fare you
well. Feb. 25.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your louing friend, WILLIAM
AMES.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:22763:29"/>
                     <head>Mercie and peace be with you, Amen.</head>
                     <p>SIr, becauſe I doe vnderſtand by many, that you maruell I
anſwer not your reaſons, hauing had your writing ſo long in mine hands, I
thought good to returne you a briefe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Your reaſons to prooue
viſible communion out of a viſible Church follow: Though that be not the
queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene you and mee, But whether we which are, or deeme our
ſelues to be of a viſible Church, may lawfully commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with ſuch as
be of no Church?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> I deny that externall
communion doth neceſſarily flowe from the diſcerning of inward communion
with Chriſt, which is your firſt reaſon; for then I haue externall
commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Angells and faithfull departed this life. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
communion is a matter of externall relation and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, vnder which men out of
the Church are not. 
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41,47.</note>The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
ſet by Chriſt and his Apoſtles is, that ſuch as receiue the word, and
are to be ſaued, ioyne themſelues foorthwith vnto the Church, and a large
remnant it is of the confuſions which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath brought into
the worlde, that men fearing God ſhould remaine out of the true Church.</p>
                     <p>For the further cleering of theſe things.</p>
                     <p>If an innocent perſon (in mine abſence) be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
from the Church, vpon the teſtimony of two or three, yet will I for order
ſake (and ſo am bound) forbeare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, till I haue
manifeſted his innocencie to the Church. On the other ſide, Though I know
ſome great wickedneſſe by a brother, which he denies, and I can not
prooue, I muſt ſtill for order ſake keepe communion with him in the
Church, till God diſcouer him. It is euident ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that in caſes I am
both to forbeare communion with a godly man, till we be orderly ioyned
together; and to keep communion with a wicked man, till we be orderly
diſ-ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                     <p>Adde vnto theſe things, that vpon this ground I may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22763:30"/> lawfully admit one out of the Church, to the Lords
Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to the choiſe of Officers cenſuring of offendors. And all other
exerciſes of externall communion: if by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Charitie I deeme
him holie in his perſon. And how can I denie him one part of externall
communion, to whom I affoord an other, but I make a ſchiſme in the
communion of Saints? and this alſo may ſerue for anſwere to the latter
part of your proofe touching viſible Churches; for they haue not onely
internall communion with Chriſt, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall alſo in the order which hee
hath ſet. For which wee ſtand, and for the want of which alone, wee
withdrawe our ſelues, as wee doe in this caſe, not daring to breake
Chriſts order for mens diſorder.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> The ſumme of the ſecond
Argument is. That becauſe it is lawfull for ſome ſuch as are not yet
members of a true Church to pray, therefore others of a Church may ioyne with
them in prayer.</p>
                     <p>I doe firſt anſwer, That men in a Church are bound to, and
from many things, wherein men not in the Church may vſe more libertie, and
vppon the ſame ground you might more ſoundly argue thus: Becauſe two or
three perſons excommunicated vppon falſe teſtimonie, may pray toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and therefore the brethren of the Church may forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with pray with them; Though
prayer bee in it ſelfe a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing, and they holie in theyr perſons
that perfourme it, yet it is vnlawfully perfourmed out of the Church, in which
men ought to bee, and therein to vſe it. So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there bee neyther
<hi>Vitium perſonae nec vitium rei.</hi> Yet is there <hi>Vitium ordinis,
&amp; relationis:</hi> and this exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall religious order, and relation is the
Church-order, and religious communion, a worke, doth preſuppoſe religious
v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of perſons.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Touching men ioyning in
prayer before they enter coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſo before they be in a Church, whence
you doe take your third Argument: I doe anſwere; Firſt, for that there is
not the like reaſon of them and vs, which are, or <pb n="51" facs="tcp:22763:30"/> take
our ſelues to bee in the order of an eſtabliſhed Church; They then breake
no order, though wee ſhould. Secondly, ſuch perſons are ioyned in will
and purpoſe at the leaſt, the which is accepted as the deed. 2.
<hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 12. though the outward ceremonie
bee not as yet performed: So is <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to haue offered vp
<hi>Iſaack, Hebrewes chapter</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 17. and
<hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila</hi> to haue laied downe their owne neckes
for <hi>Paules</hi> life, <hi>Rom. chapter</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4.
Which notwithſtanding they did onely in will and purpoſe. Your axiom
<hi>à velle ad eſſe non ſequitur ratio,</hi> hath his vſe
eſpecially <hi>in rebus naturalibus.</hi> But the vrging of it thus
abſolutely in matters of religion, tends to depriue the Church of her
greateſt ſpirituall comfort. Laſtly, conſider the couenant <hi>in
concrete,</hi> and prayer is a part thereof. And when men are ſo met, with a
purpoſe to vnite, and do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne prayer for the ſanctification of it: They
are in the doore comming into the houſe, and not without. The Iewes were not
to haue religious communion with perſons vncircumciſed, and yet I doubt
not, but when a godlie Proſelite was to be circumciſed, they might lawfully
ioyne with him for the ſanctification of the Ordinaunce. I ceaſe further to
trouble you, and doe heartily ſalute you in the Lord God, wiſhing you from
him all proſperitie; and in him reſting.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Leyden 
<date>this ſecond of the weeke</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your louing friend IOHN
ROBINSON.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:22763:31"/>
                     <p>SIr, I did maruell indeed at your ſilence, when an anſwer
was promiſed, &amp; do no leſſe maruell at this your anſwer, that being
ſo deliberate, it is no more ſound and pertinent. As for the ſtate of the
queſtion, it was ſet downe in your owne wordes (thus in the theſis,
Whether there be viſible communion out of a viſible Church) not to bee
denyed or diſſembled in this your anſwere, as it is more than once, when
you would draw it to an hypotheſis. In the anſwer to the firſt Argument,
your denial is very ſtrange, &amp; the reaſons of it as weake. The
Scripture doth euery where reaſon from that communion which we haue with
Chriſt to that which we ought to haue one with another. Our beſt Diuines
doe put one in the definition of the other. <hi>Sanctorum communio eſt actus
&amp; officium ſingulorum membrorum inter ſe, ez vnione formali cum
Chriſto, &amp; ſpiritu ipſius profluens:</hi> the ſence is
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all good writers: The words are taken from reuerend
<hi>Iunius.</hi> The ſame ſentence is elſewhere by him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
ſo fitly for you (if you doe not deſpiſe it) that I hope it may
ſomething preuaile with you. <hi>Ex illa autem ſocietate</hi> (ſaith hee)
<hi>&amp; communione quam Sancti cum Chriſto habent, omnino ſequitur altera
haec conſociatio atque communio qua membra inter ſe conſociata &amp;
coagmentata ſunt: nam idem qui nos adunauit ſibi eo ipſo quod diuerſa
membra adunat ſibi, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem inter ſe adunauit: quae cum it a ſint, facile
Chriſtianus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet nobis aſſenſurus eſt ſi imperturbato animo ad
haec legenda &amp; expendenda venerit, non poſſe quenquam Chriſtianum
bona fide renunciare communioni alterius, quem Chriſtus aut ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>unxit ſibi, aut ſe adiuncturum
ſpem facit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The place note well worth your ſerious reading: Reaſon
ſhewes the ſame truth. For, are you more holy than Chriſt, that you
ſhould beate him from your communion, whome Chriſt hath made a member of
his body? doth not our inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall communion one with an other flow from that
internall communion we haue with Chriſt? Whence then doth our externall flow
but from that externall which wee haue with <pb n="53" facs="tcp:22763:31"/> him; or (which
is the ſame) from viſible diſcerning of that internall?</p>
                     <p>Your inſtances of Angells and Saints departed doe make
directly againſt you; for we doe not viſibly and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerne
of them and their communion with Chriſt: but in extraordinarie caſes, and
at ſuch times, we may haue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible communion with them. When the
heauenly company did celebrate the birth of our Sauiour, ſaying, <hi>Glorie
bee to God on high, &amp;c.</hi> I hope you will not ſay it had beene ſinne
for the Sheepheards to ſay Amen to it; nor for the Diſciples to haue giuen
the like aſſent to any worſhip perfourmed by thoſe which came out of
their graues at the reſurrection of Chriſt. Your other inſtance of an
innocent excommunicate hath no force at all; for your ſelfe doe not ſay,
that it is not ſimply vnlawfull to haue any communion with him at all: but
onely for ſome time: nor that <hi>co nomine,</hi> becauſe he is out of the
Church, but for order ſake. Now I do not ſpeake of ſuch a neceſſitie
as bindeth <hi>ſemper &amp; ad ſemper,</hi> neyther am I againſt the
confederacie of circumſtances; but conſider it ſimply (ſcandall and
contempt remoued) it is lawfull to communicate with ſuch a one.</p>
                     <p>As for that conſequence of yours, If one part of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
then to all: It doth better ſerue the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
children from Baptiſme, than you to exclude Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from priuate
communion, becauſe you will not admit them to ſome part of the publique. He
that can ſpie ſchiſme in admitting to one part before, then to all, might
farre more eaſily ſee the ſame, in excluding viſible Chriſtians from
all, if he were not ſome way blinded: For is it not a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous breach of
charitie to afford no more communion to a true Chriſtian, than to a Turke?
Your reaſon which you giue of hauing communion with viſible Churches,
becauſe they haue externall communion with Chriſt in the order which hee
hath ſet, doeth not infringe, but confirme my proofe; for whence hath that
order this force of drawing anie to communion? becauſe that is a ſigne of
inward true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. <pb n="54" facs="tcp:22763:32"/> Whereſoeuer then there is
euident diſcerning of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, there outward is lawfull.</p>
                     <p>I am not ignorant of ſome circumſtantiall expediences
which tie thoſe that liue in well ordered Aſſemblies, more than other
men; but (to omit that the queſtion is generall, not onely of ſuch) There
is nothing ſimply vnlawfull to one in the nature of it (at leaſt to giue
aſſent to) that is lawfull for an other: neyther can there bee any
inſtance giuen of an action lawfull in one to performe, which is vnlawfull
for anie other to aſſent vnto. That of excommunication I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
before.</p>
                     <p>Your firſt anſwere to the third Argument is beſides the
queſtion, which in your owne words is generall of any: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is a
very ſtrange order that is broken, by ſaying A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to a godly mans prayer,
the Scripture knoweth no ſuch I am ſure. In the ſecond, you miſtake
that reaſon, from the will to the deed. For howſoeuer before God in
ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions it ſo holdeth; yet before men, eſpecially in
priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges belonging to any outward ſocietie; it nothing auaileth to make
profeſſion of ſuch a deſire. But if it doth as you ſay, then doth it
great wrong vnto all good Chriſtians, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them communion, who
profeſſe they deſire to ioyne in all the ordinances of God, ſo farre as
they can diſcerne them. So whereas you ſay, that ſuch as intend a
couenant, are in the doore; I hope all conuerted Chriſtians are at the
leaſt in the doore of the true Church: or if you make the doore ſo narrow,
I nothing doubt but ye may goe into the Porch and Court of the Lords houſe to
take a godly man by the hand.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things conſidered I am halfe perſwaded, that you
will confeſſe your ſelfe to haue ſinned in ſeparating thoſe whome
God hath ioyned together in communion, That is, all viſible Saints; which God
of his mercie graunt.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your true friend William Ames.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:22763:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. To the right Reuerend, master <hi>Francis
Iohnſon</hi> our Pastor, with the other Elders his Aſsistants, Our
ouerſeers, grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing, beloued, that we are fallen into peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous daies,
ſome faining vnto themſelues one religion, and ſome another; and
becauſe the right way is a ſtrait way, euery one whoſe way is ſtrait,
doth thinke that they haue that right way. And conſidering the many ſorts
of the ſeparation at this day, curſing or reiecting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: others
thinking but baſely one of another; as to begin with our ſelues, whom
maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his followers hath left and reiected as
falſe Chriſtians; maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but key-cold
brother-hood with vs, and maſter <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> and he, and we
iarring about ruling Elders; thoſe in Suffolke holding it vnlawfull to eat
blood; and to flie (as we haue heard) <hi>Iohn Wilkinſon</hi> and his
diſciples will haue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Thomas Leamar</hi> will haue no
Churches, with other his wicked differences.</p>
                     <q> 
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="heresy">
                                 <head>The hereſie of one <hi>Thomas Lemar,</hi>
deſcribed by master <hi>Padget,</hi> with this title: The Monster of
Lemariſme.</head>
                                 <p>THis Monſter was ſet forth with ſeuen heads.</p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>1 <hi>Mahometiſme,</hi> in that <hi>Lemar</hi>
denied the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and the eternall God-head of Chriſt.</item>
                                    <item> 2 <hi>Iudaiſme,</hi> in affirming that
Chriſt ſhould come ſhortly in his owne perſon, to raigne heere vpon
earth.</item>
                                    <item> 
                                       <pb n="56" facs="tcp:22763:33"/>3 <hi>Papiſme,</hi> in
holding that a meere creature is to bee worſhipped.</item>
                                    <item> 4 <hi>Lutheraniſme,</hi> in maintaining the
doctrine of Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</item>
                                    <item> 5 <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> in affirming that
Chriſt tooke not his fleſh of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item> 6 <hi>Libertiniſme,</hi> in holding that there
is no viſible Church now on earth.</item>
                                    <item> 7 <hi>Browniſme,</hi> in holding the doctrine
of their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> an Anabaptiſt of one ſort, and
maſter <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> of another, and maſter <hi>Buſher</hi> of
another. <hi>Iohn Hancock</hi> wil haue a ſeparation by himſelfe. The
ground of maſter <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils</hi> errors was alſo ſeparation; though now
hee bee further runne backward then euer he was forward; to ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
of <hi>Pedder, Henrie Martin,</hi> with the reſt of thoſe
<hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists.</hi> Theſe are motiues forwarding our meditations this way
together with our mortalitie, and the iuſtice of God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſin, ſo
that we dare not deferre to make knowne our repentance vnto you, for the
ſpace of an houre longer: we might note the hand of God againſt vs in our
eſtates, a iuſt puniſhment for ſin, by the law of God. The thing then
is this; whereas ſome yeares ſince our minds were much affected and
troubled with the horride eſtate of the Churches of our natiue countrey, and
whileſt wee were thus muſing many wayes, and reading ſuch bookes as came
to our hands, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other we light vpon ſome booke of this cauſe,
laying open more corruptions in all eſtates, and that with more
ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie and plaineneſſe (as we thought): ſo ſtill the way was
prepared vnto Separation, and we pricked forward as with ſpurres and goads.
But then inſiſting further, that the Church of England was a falſe
Church, and that knowne ſin not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out doth defile the whole Church, as
leauen doth the lumpe, and we perceiuing ſo much ſowre dowe, we needed no
eloquent Rhetoritian to perſwade vs vnto ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For had thoſe two
things been true, and a iealous eye and heart <pb n="57" facs="tcp:22763:33"/> making them
his obiect, it would not make them go but run to ſeparation, and to be as the
Hee-goats before the flocke, ſo haue wee done vntill of late, and perſwaded
as many to follow vs as we could, if they looke or hope for ſaluation: the
Lord pardon vs for it. But ſeeing that the diſcouerie of the Churches of
England to bee falſe Churches, is now by our ſelues diſcouered to be but
a fiction, we cannot perceiue but that our Separation in that behalfe is at an
end: for, the cauſe being remoued, the effects muſt needs vaniſh; and
ſo in thoſe two reſpects it repenteth vs that we haue ſeparated. And
ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence that repentance cannot be knowne to be ſincere, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be
ſhewed forth by action, or ſpeech, or both: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this writing we
do make it knowne, &amp; by voice &amp; by our actions we ſhall make it
knowne, as God ſhall miniſter iuſt occaſion. Thus (Reuerend and well
beloued) in treathing you to reade this vnto the Church, or to deliuer the
whole ſubſtance of it by ſpeech, that they may take knowledge of it,
leſt we be blamed of many hereafter that we did not make our minds knowne
vnto them, we ceaſe, praying the Lord to ſhew vs all mercie to go with a
ſteedie foot in the truth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The eighth of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1611. new
ſtile.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>By two of your feeble flocke, fearefull any
longer to go astray. 
<list>
                              <item>MAT. SAVNDERS.</item>
                              <item>CVTH. HVTTEN.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:22763:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. The testimonie of <hi>W. Simſon</hi> againſt the
Prophets in maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> Church.</head>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="testimony">
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued and reuerend in the Lord, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
of our eſtate, doth ſo diſquiet my conſcience and trouble my mind, that
indeed I can haue no reſolution of peace in my thoughts thereabout. The
firſt maine cauſe of this griefe is, our reiecting communion with all the
reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on earth, and all true Chriſtians in the ſame; euen
thoſe whom our ſelues do account true Churches, we do yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and
ſeparate from their communion: this practiſe can haue no warrant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods
word. And for the reproofe of our ſeueritie in this euill courſe;
conſider how you called maſter <hi>Abram</hi> to repentance for ioyning to
the Dutch Church of London, and how neuer a word was ſpoken of thoſe great
ſcandals he fell into before, vpon which he departed and left the Church.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, as wee deſpiſe all other worſhip in true
Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo our own maner of exerciſe on the Lords day, is with ſuch
confuſion and contradicting one another, ſo that euen our owne
profeſſion of ſeparation is indeed quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne thereby: for
example, <hi>Thomas Cocky</hi> in his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, witneſſing againſt
England, ſaith their miniſterie is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, and being ſo they
can beget no true faith, and no true faith can haue no true ſaluation, and
ſo conſequently in the Church of England is taught no ſaluation (a
fearefull ſentence in my iudgement.) Againe, our beloued maſter <hi>de
Cluſe</hi> in his doctrine of propheſie, laboured to proue ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
from a true Church for any corruption obſtinately flood in; this doctrine was
by another in propheſying then ſhewed to be abſolutely contrary to that
place of <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.24. <pb n="59" facs="tcp:22763:34"/> which how vnſoundly it was
concluded by our Teacher, was then obſerued by many. Alſo it was ſince by
another deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the way of propheſie, that euen amongſt our ſelues
did raigne many ſins, as namely, fulneſſe of bread, pride, and
idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; fulneſſe of bread, in that many were not ſatisfied with
neither ſpirituall nor temporall food; pride, in that many did ſtriue to go
aboue their calling; idleneſſe, in that many were negligent in their
calling. If theſe things be ſo, and be not redreſſed by the admonition
of this propheſie, wee muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to maſter <hi>de Cluſe</hi> his
doctrine make a new ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: how oft do the Brethren except one againſt
another for their doctrine, whereby much heart-burning and ſtrife is kindled
betwixt them? Theſe things being well conſidered, I entreate you well to
mind whether this new way of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying on the Lords day can bee for the
edification of the Church, or not?</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. Of the diſſenſion betweene <hi>Iohn
Iohnſon</hi> the father, and <hi>Francis</hi> the ſonne: and betwixt the
bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Francis.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the writings and dealings of <hi>George Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
there appeares more ſimplicitie &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then in
<hi>Francis,</hi> whoſe politique ſhifts and courſes are as the way of an
<hi>Eagle,</hi> in the ayre: now ſuch courſes are much to be
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, whereas commonly plaine dealing and honeſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are as
louing companions, that go hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. To omit manifold inſtances
of this crooked and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dealing of <hi>Francis Iohnſon,</hi> let this
one authentique teſtimony thereof, giuen both by the French and Dutch
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, deputed of their Presbiteries to be conſidered
indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:22763:35"/> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="testimony">
                              <p>Narrauit nobis <hi>Ioannes Ianſonius</hi> Anglus,
ſe hominem ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagenarium ex Anglia in hanc vrbem difficili itinere
veniſſe vt duos filios ſuos <hi>Franciſcum</hi> &amp; <hi>Georgium
Ianſonios</hi> diſsidentes, quorum ille pastorem agit coetus Anglici, qui
degit apud nos, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> ab eodem coetu
excommunicatus est, in gratiam reduceret: quum<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> hoc negotium
reconciliationis ageret, incidiſſe ſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſiam cum filio ſuo
<hi>Franciſco</hi> &amp; ſenioribus toto<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> caetu cui praeeſt ille,
cui componendae commodius remedium inuenire non potuiſſe dixit, quam ſi
ſe ad Belgicam &amp; Gallicam Eccleſias, quae in hac vrbe ſunt,
conſilij auxilij<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> cauſâ conferret. Quâ cauſâ
petijt à nobis vt ipſi conſilio &amp; ope noſtra adeſſe
vellemus, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittens controuerſiam totam iudicio arbitrario duarum
praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarum Eccleſiarum. Nos vero honeſti ſenis petitioni id
conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum putauimus vt à <hi>Franciſco</hi> &amp; nonnullis
ſenioribus coetus Anglicani ſupra dicti peteremus, an etiam parati
eſſent eandem controuerſiam arbitrario earundem Eccleſiarum aut
ſynedrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vtriuſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> iudicio ſummittere? cui quaeſtioni, licet
multis id conati ſumus, responſum Categoricum obtinere ab illis
nequiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Quod cum videremus, exiſtimauimus nos nihil porro apud illos in
hoc negotio effecturos. Cuius rei teſtimonium petenti <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anni
Ianſonio</hi> denegare noluimus. Actum Amstelredami in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deputatos
ſynedrij Eccleſiae vtriuſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> Belgicae &amp; Gallicae octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo
Nouembris anni milleſimi ſexcenteſimi ſecundi, ſtilo nouo.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed> 
                                    <list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Ioannes</hi> à <hi>Vinea</hi> in
Eccleſia Gallobelgica Miniſter Euangelij.</item>
                                       <item> 
                                          <hi>Petrus Plancius</hi> adminiſter
Euangelij.</item>
                                       <item> 
                                          <hi>Iacobus Arminius</hi> adminiſter
Euangelij in Eccleſia Belgica.</item>
                                       <item> 
                                          <hi>Simon Goulartius</hi> adminiſter verbi
in Eccleſia Gallobelgica.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Francis Iohnſon</hi> excommunicateth his father and
brother.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 TO curſe any man raſhly and vniuſtly, is
ſinne; but to curſe parents is more vile.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 But in M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> the pure Separatiſt,
father of the Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcan order, for him to curſe his own father is yet
more vile.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 When hee did this, and drew his whole company to
conſent and approue thereof, it was the more vile, for poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning others
with his ſin.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:22763:35"/>4 This curſe being not a common
reproch or euil ſpeech, but the heauie curſe of excommunication in giuing
his father to the diuell: is not this more fearefull?</p>
                  <p n="5">5 This cenſure giuen out vpon ſo ſleight a
cauſe, yea ſo vniuſt a cauſe, while the father ſought peace betwixt
his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; was it not the more horrible for the ſon ſo to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
the father a ſtranger, ſo to condemne him for conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that paſſed
the ſeas only to make peace?</p>
                  <p n="6">6 This done ſo violently and cruelly, that no aduice,
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, no nor threats of the Dutch Church might reſtraine or ſtay the
rage of Saint <hi>Francis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7 This done againſt ſuch a father as had bin at ſo
great coſt in bringing vp his ſon to learning, &amp; he to vſe his
Sophiſtrie, euen againſt his Father: how vile!</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Thus to iudge and condemne his father, who alſo with
ſo much labor, coſt and griefe had ſued to ſundry Iudges and nobles in
England for releaſing of that ſon; as may appear by the generall copies of
thoſe humble petitions and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi>
made for his ſons <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>George</hi> vnto the high
Commiſſioners; and to others.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, in that M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> did thus proceed to
exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat his father, after he had before co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned his brother
<hi>George,</hi> this alſo doth aggrauate his offence: for the reiection of
his brother firſt might ſomething haue ſoftened his heart, and the
conſcience thereof might haue ſtaied him from grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter crueltie towards his
father.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, in that M. <hi>Francis</hi> did continue &amp;
perſiſt obſtinatly vnto the death of his father without reuocation of his
error, or reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation to his father, ſending his father downe to the graue
with this curſe vpon his backe, rolling the ſtone of his cenſure vpon the
graues mouth, ſealing it vp with his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, as it were engrauing the
ſentence of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication for an Epitaph vpon his fathers tombe; in all
this he hath filled the meaſure of his iniquity, and ſo encreaſed both
the height of his ſin, and waight of his iudgement, vnleſſe in time he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge himſelfe and repent his
wickedneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:22763:36"/>
                  <head>How they curſe and excommunicate one another.</head>
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Smith</hi> in his 
<note n="a" place="margin">Epiſtle to the
Reader.</note>Character of the beaſt, comparing himſelfe vnto
<hi>Caligula</hi> a monſtrous beaſt, vſeth theſe words touching them of
the Separation; <hi>I could wiſh</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>as the tyrant
wiſhed concerning the people of Rome, that all their heads were ioyned into
one, and all their ſtrength compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into one writing, that with the
ſword of the Spirit, it might be ſmitten off at once, &amp;c.</hi> As
maſter <hi>Smith</hi> wiſhed to be, ſo hath maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi>
laboured to be, euen as <hi>Caligula,</hi> or as <hi>Nero,</hi> and worſe
than <hi>Nero.</hi> It is recorded of <hi>Nero,</hi> That hee ſet Rome on
fire, that in the meane time hee might ſing <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers verſes</hi> which
hee made vpon the burning of <hi>Troy.</hi> But maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi>
hath ſet Ieruſalem on fire, by kindling the wilde fire of Separation, euen
vpon true Churches, through his ſchiſmaticall doctrine, that in the meane
time he might ſing the wordes of the Angell, ſpoken vpon the deſtruction
of Rome, ſaying; <hi>It is fallen, it is fallen, Babylon that great, &amp;c.
Nero</hi> is ſaid to haue ſlaine his owne mother, and to haue ript vp her
belly, to look into her wombe, where once hee had laine; <hi>Francis
Iohnſon</hi> is ſaid to haue ſlaine his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſword of
Excommunication, and with the knife of his ſharpe ſchiſme to haue
ſlaine his mother church, and to haue rent and ript open her wombe, wherein
hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth himſelfe to haue beene regenerate and borne anew.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> is ſaid to haue ſlaine <hi>Seneca</hi> the
Philoſopher his maſter, that taught him: S. <hi>Francis</hi> with the
ſword of his cenſure, hath cut off all his Teachers in England, that
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him in learning, hath alſo cut off his ſpeciall Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher M.
<hi>Ainſworth,</hi> and depoſed him from his office, though once he
prayſed him as 
<note n="b" place="margin">Preface to D.B. Sect. 1.</note>
                     <hi>his
worke-fellow to the Kingdome of God.</hi> And further, as thoſe Tyrants
<hi>Caligula</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> did rage cruelly and ſtrangely towards
their owne kindred, ſo haue theſe Separatiſts done the like: for whom
will they <pb n="63" facs="tcp:22763:36"/> ſpare that ſpare not their owne parents? If
wee make a computation of the perſons that haue beene led into this Schiſme
of <hi>Browniſme,</hi> we ſhall not find one of tenne, but their curſe is
lying vpon them. Yea, there is not a <hi>Browniſt</hi> aliue this day, but
either hee hath (or at leaſt by their rule ſhould haue) the curſe lying
vpon his head, and his commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion auoided as an vncleane thing; euery one is
deuouring another, euery one eating the fleſh off his brothers arme, and
euery one drunken with anothers bloud. As for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient companie of the
<hi>Browniſts,</hi> that were vnder the feeding of <hi>Browne</hi>
himſelfe, thoſe that curſed the reprouers of pride therein, <hi>were
ſwept away as dung</hi> by the teſtimonie of <hi>George Iohnſon,</hi> and
not one of them aliue in his time that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued faithfull, but became
Apoſtataes. Not to ſpeake of the manifold curſes that flew abroad in the
time of <hi>Barrow,</hi> nor yet of the manifold curſes which the companie of
the <hi>Browniſts</hi> remayning in London haue oft layed vpon one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
one halfe deuouring another at once; conſider thoſe that remaine in theſe
parts of the Low Countries at this time.</p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his companie are now accurſed and
auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his companie.</p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his companie are againe reiected
and auoided by M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his.</p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Smith</hi> and his companie are reiected both of M.
<hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and M. <hi>Ainſworth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> and his companie holding M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his to be in Apoſtaſie by their owne grounds, muſt
auoid them.</p>
                  <p>And M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> him againe, for taking part with M.
<hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> in his Schiſme againſt him.</p>
                  <p>And by this reckoning, where is there one of them that can
lift vp his head this day without a curſe vpon it? Which of them can ſay, I
am free from the curſe? As for thoſe ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Browniſts</hi> that
walke alone, as they auoid all, ſo are they auoided and reiected by all the
reſt. Is not this a curſing <pb n="64" facs="tcp:22763:37"/> and a curſed generation,
curſed euen by their owne mouth, by their owne ſentence, by their owne
rules both of doctrine and practiſe.</p>
                  <p>But of all the ſeparation, it is M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> that
hath the haughtie eyes aboue them all; it is S. <hi>Francis,</hi> whoſe
loftie lookes are noted and obſerued of thoſe that know him and haue to
deale with him. Maſter <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> though a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſt, yet is
he well knowne to be farre more moderate in his carriage, and lookes not halfe
ſo high. Maſter <hi>Clifton,</hi> though a Teacher of the
<hi>Franciſcanes,</hi> yet is he knowne to be farre from the arrogancie of
the other; yea, he is pitied as being a bondſlaue vnto S. <hi>Francis.</hi>
Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though drunken with the dregges of error,
and ſtrange phantaſies (the beginning and ground whereof he boaſteth to
haue ſucked from his tutor S. <hi>Francis</hi>) yet is he in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour
nothing ſo haughtie and proud, as his Tutor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelfe: But for
further proofe of the vncouth pride and arrogancie of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> let
vs heare the teſtimonie of his owne father.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="testimony">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Iohn Iohnſons</hi> writing, the Father of
<hi>Francis Iohnſon.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>SOnne, you asked me alſo in the preſence of M.
<hi>Studley,</hi> Wherein you were vnnaturall? I anſwere you by theſe
things following, you vrging me thereto.</p>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 That I comming in my old age ſo farre, ſo
hard and dangerous a iourney to ſeeke and make peace betweene you, the Church
and your brother, I could neuer ſee the leaſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in you to peace:
neither tendered you my old age, but ſo vſed me, as if God ſtrengthened
not me, you might preſently bring my gray haires with ſorrow to the
graue.</item>
                                 <item> 2 Lodging in your houſe the first weeke, you
were ſo far from peace, and ſo vnkindly vſed me, that you made me weary
before the weeke was ended: ſo was I forced to ſhift to my other ſonnes
lodging.</item>
                                 <item> 
                                    <pb n="65" facs="tcp:22763:37"/>3 When I dealt with you for
peace, you ſought to catch and enſnare me in my words, and afterward (as I
perceiued) alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Elders, and the people to the like
dealing.</item>
                                 <item> 4 You vpbraided me with things ſecret betweene
me and my childe in the Country, which were vntrue, and if they had beene true,
you ought not to diſgrace mee, as <hi>Cham</hi> did, <hi>Geneſis 9.</hi>
You did worſe than hee did, but God haue praiſe, they were not true: yet
your vnnaturall and vnchristian dealing appeared herein both in vpbrayding mee
vntruely and vniustly, and if it had beene true, ſo to doe, it is as to vex
and diſgrace me.</item>
                                 <item> 5 To let me ſtand two houres on my feet before
you and the people, and your ſelfe ſate all the time, and not once bid mee
ſit downe your ſelfe, neyther ſpeake to the people to bid me.</item>
                                 <item> 6 Not once in the ſpace of ſix weekes did
you come to viſite me, or aske how I did, being in the ſame Citie with you,
and hauing come ſo farre for your peace.</item>
                                 <item> 7 You denied to giue me your hand vnto that,
which before you had graunted to others.</item>
                                 <item> 8 You would not truſt my word; but forced me
to proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</item>
                                 <item> 9 Theſe, and ſuch like things made mee call
to minde your vnnaturalneſſe, that in the ſpace of fiue yeares and more,
you had not written to mee that you were deſirous to ſee my face, or that I
ſhould be welcome to you, when I wrote to you of my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in comming: So
little thankefulneſſe and nature haue you ſhewed vnto me, for all my care
and paines for you from your youth, and I feare your example will make many
fathers (if they be not vpright-hearted) to hold their children from learning
and ſtudying in the Vniuerſities.</item>
                                 <item> 10 You heard me ſcoffed and gibed by diuers in
the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and not once rebuked them; which many children not
profeſsing godlineſſe, but led onely by nature, would not haue indured to
heare against their father.</item>
                                 <item> 11 But no wonder, for at length you became ſo
hardned, that you ſate as principall, and heard your father excommunicated,
being come to be a peace-maker. Hath the like vnnaturalneſſe beene read or
heard of?</item>
                                 <item> 
                                    <pb n="66" facs="tcp:22763:38"/>12 Comming afterward to you,
and talking with you, you ſaid you might not keepe company with mee: doth
Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation cut off dueties of children to fathers? &amp;c. </item>
                              </list>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. A taſte of their deteſtable ſlaunders and
reproches concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church of England.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
                  <hi>Generation, whoſe teeth are as ſwordes, and their
iawes as kniues.</hi> By lying, ſlaundering, and ſcorning, their teeth are
as ſwords to wound others, and their iawes, as kniues, to eate vp and deuoure
one an other among themſelues. For example; in <hi>Barrow;</hi> to note a few
of his outragious ſpeeches; he telleth vs concerning the Church of England; 
<note place="margin">Diſco. pa. 9.</note>
                  <hi>That whether wee
conſider the whole estate, or any particular part thereof, wee ſhall finde
it wholy corrupt and deepely ſet as in the dayes of</hi> Gibeah, &amp;c. 
<note place="margin">Pag 10.</note>
                  <hi>There is no faith, no mercy,
no knowledge, or feare of God in the land &amp;c. Neyther <hi rend="sup">a</hi> hath all kind of
ſinne and wickednes more <hi rend="sup">b</hi> vniuerſally <hi rend="sup">c</hi> raigned in <hi rend="sup">d</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nation, at <hi rend="sup">e</hi>
any time, than here at this preſent in this land; &amp;c.</hi> Behold fiue
notable lies in one line.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note>And hauing mentioned their
gouernement he ſaith; <hi>Now vnto this theyr Apostaticall and bloody throne,
and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian power, and vnto all the abhominations, proceeding from the
ſame ſtandeth all the land both great and ſmall, rich and poore priest
and people, in most ſeruile ſubiection: and therefore in this estate cannot
be held or numbred among Chriſts faithfull ſeruants, which are fully
redeemed by the price of his precious blood, &amp;c.</hi> And thus this foule
mouth yelleth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 141.</note>Touching the Miniſters he
ſaith; <hi>Likewiſe if I ſhould heere ſtand to relate the falſhood,
deceit, and hypocriſie of theſe prieſts (let me here be vnderstood euen
of thoſe beſt-eſteemed, forward <pb n="67" facs="tcp:22763:38"/> learned Preachers,
commonly called good men) how cunningly and craftily they teach the Lawe; neuer
touching or offending theyr Auditory (at least the mighty or rich of them) bee
theyr ſinnes neuer ſo heynous and manifest; especially if they will
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, esteeme, feast and heare theſe Preachers, they are in them but
infirmities and imperfections, be they neuer ſo deepely ſet and
incurable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the Vniuerſities of Cambridge and Oxford
<hi>Barrow</hi> ſaith; <hi>They are like vnto the Popes Seminaries, beeing as
ready vpon the least change of the weather now to ſerue him as euer they
were:</hi> How did <hi>Barrow</hi> know their hearts, that he could ſlaunder
men for things to be done in time to come vpon occaſion of danger? Could the
father of lies himſelfe vtter a more preſumptuous lie than this his
diſciple?</p>
               <p>In fine, to omit hundreds of ſuch raylings and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
ſpeeches; when he ſpeaketh of the Churches or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples where they meete to
worſhip God, hee calleth them <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll Synagogues, abhominable
ſties,</hi> the Pulpit hee calleth a <hi>Priuiledged Table;</hi> their
Baptiſme hee calleth <hi>Adulterate Baptiſme;</hi> the Lordes Supper, as it
is there adminiſtred, a <hi>Two penny feast,</hi> a <hi>She ſhake
ſupper,</hi> the word preached, he calleth, <hi>Preachments and
Sermocinations;</hi> The People and Miniſters he calleth <hi>Babyloniſh
reprobate ſtones, Sodomits, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites, Balaamites, Chamites, Kainites;</hi>
here is a <hi>Diabolus</hi> indeede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ainſworth</hi> excuſeth theſe belliſh raylings, and
cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them but ſeuere ſpeeches; and againe addeth alſo, <hi>I
ſuppoſe you can hardly ſhew any hard ſpeech that Master</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<hi>there writeth, which the Prophets and Apostles haue not vſed before.</hi>
Maſter <hi>Smith alſo calleth it</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Paralel p. 134.</note> 
                  <hi>Master</hi>
Barrowes <hi>Tarteneſſe, whereas he might more iustly haue called it Adder
poyſon, and the Gall of Aspes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> ſaith; 
<note place="margin">Pag. 84.</note>
                  <hi>That hee knew not by what
particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar motion of the Spirit hee was guided to write in thoſe
phraſes.</hi> But maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> iuſtifieth further, to make
good Maiſter <hi>Smiths</hi> and his owne dotage, by adding theſe words;
<hi>espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <pb n="68" facs="tcp:22763:39"/> conſidering with what fire and zeale the
Lord hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſuch his ſeruants at all times, as hee hath
ſtirred vp for ſpeciall reformation. Let the example of</hi> Luther
<hi>alone ſuffice, whome into what termes his zeale carried him his writings
doe teſtifie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For further declaration of their lying and reprochfull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
let this teſtimonie following concerning the ſlaunders of <hi>Samuel
Wats</hi> and <hi>Francis Iohnſon</hi> be heere conſidered of the
Reader.</p>
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="testimony">
                           <p>I Was certified <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> long
ſithence of a vaine ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor ſpred of mee in England, as if I had ioyned with
the Schiſme of them, who are commonly called <hi>Browniſts.</hi> This
report was much ſtrengthened (as I was then informed) by the ſlanders of
one <hi>Samuel Wats,</hi> who gaue forth about Sarum, that I had read or
ſeene the phantaſticall booke which he a little before had printed: a fond
and friuolous vntruth, yet ſo preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ſome, forgetting the
Commaundement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not receiue a falſe tale againſt thy
neighbour,</hi> as that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my depriuation was haſtened. The truth is,
that receiuing commendations by him from ſome of my acquaintance (not well
acquainted, as it ſeemeth, with the vanitie of the man) I spoke with him
once; afterward inquiring of him, I forbore euer to ſee him: yea, more I
dealt by my friend, with the Printer, to haue his booke ſtayed; which I could
not obtaine, the Printer anſwering, that the bargaine was alreadie made, and
a good part of the money aforehand receiued. Now it grieued me not at this time
a little that Sathan ſhould be ſo impudent, as to fling the dung of that
Sect into my face, which with all my power I had ſo vehemently reſiſted,
during the whole courſe of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie in England: howbeit I comforted
my ſelfe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and continuall loue of Gods ſeruants, walking
through good and through euill report before me. Since I haue of late receiued
freſh newes by M. <hi>Michael Seroyen,</hi> my good friend, That this report
(which ſhould not by right haue liued longer than the lye of the Gibeonites)
runneth ſtill on foot, euen to this <pb n="69" facs="tcp:22763:39"/> houre.
<hi>Hanniball</hi> ſaid once, there was not ſo much as one in all the
enemies Campe that was called <hi>Giſco;</hi> ſo may it truly bee ſaid
now; not ſo much as one of the godly Miniſters that ſuffer in England
about the diſcipline, that may deſeruedly be called a <hi>Browniſt.</hi>
The harder is my hap that I ſhould be reputed one of them, who am ioyned
againſt them with that Orthodox Church here, which like a beautifull armie,
and terrible, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tents, and lyeth in the field (and that with happie and
good ſucceſſe) againſt that Schiſme. I thinke no other, but that
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them loue the Lord, and feare his name: howbeit, their error being
enemy to that breaſt of Charity wherewith <hi>Cyprian</hi> couered his,
<hi>Qui ab Eccleſia nunquam receſſit,</hi> as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
ſpeaketh: They can not ſtand before his Tribunall, but by the
interceſsion of our bleſſed Sauiour, Father, forgiue them, they know not
what they doe. Thinke not theſe wordes are applied to theyr ſect
amiſſe: for in effect what doeth it leſſe than euen perſecute the
Lord Chriſt Ieſus in his hoste, which it reuileth, in his ordinaunces which
it diſhonoureth, and in his ſeruants laſt of all, whoſe graces it
blasphemeth, whoſe foote ſteppes it ſlaundereth, and whoſe perſons it
dispiſeth; and that well neare with the pride of <hi>Aceſius,</hi> to whome
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> once. <hi>Scalas ſume Aceſi &amp; ſolus in Coelum
aſcende.</hi> This is found in ſpeciall manner in Maister
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany aboue the reſt, whoſe ſpirites are
bitter aboue meaſure, and hearts puffed vp with the Leauen of Pride, and
whoſe walking is ſo crooked, and built on ſuch grounds of coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
deceipt and guile, that out of <hi>Salomon</hi> it may not vnfitly be
reſembled, to the way of a Serpent vppon a ſtone. He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe defameth
mee, without cauſe, without colour, without ceaſing hee arraigneth my Booke
in open Conſiſtory, and there ſitting magiſtrate-like hee demaundeth of
mee, though abſent, wherefore he may not alleadge, <hi>Hoſea</hi> chap. 14.
ver. 92.2. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint.</hi> chap. 6. ver. 16. <hi>Iohn</hi> chap. 5. ver. 21.
againſt the Church of England, as well as I haue done in the beginning of my
booke? As if theſe Scriptures were not pregnant againſt communion with
Antichriſt in the vſe of his Idolles, which are by him <pb n="70" facs="tcp:22763:40"/>
vniuſtly wreſted againſt communion with a true and a Chriſtian Church,
in the holy things of God? He that wringeth the noſe, <hi>ſaith Solon,</hi>
cauſeth blood to come forth, and he that charneth milke, bringeth forth whey.
A fit reſemblance of Browniſts ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, whoſe forced allegations of
the Scripture, charne and wring it, for the bringing forth of bloody
contentions, rents, and ſchiſmes, I ſay bloody in the ſenſe of
<hi>Iſay</hi> and <hi>Hoſea;</hi> and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the wholeſome milke
thereof, ordained for the growth of the Saints in peace, and in comfort, and in
the ioy of the holy Ghoſt, into a bitter and ſowre humor, as
diſtaſtefull to the Lord, as it is diſgracefull to his Church and
ſeruants. Howbeit I purpoſe not to dispute the caſe, onely thus much
(good Reader) I thought needfull to make knowne to thee, for the clearing of
theſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, wherewith I am vniuſtly burthened. Farewell.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>ROBERT PARKER.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. Concerning their mutuall reproches,
diſſenſions and curſes against one another: diuided into three
parts.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>PART. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing ſeene the reproach which this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
ſlanderers layeth vpon others which condemne their ſeparation; let vs
conſider how they whet their teeth againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mutually.</p>
                  <p>To begin with maſter <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and to let him haue
the firſt place in reproching, and the preheminence in biting, he telleth
maſter <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> and his companie, that they are 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22763:40"/> Schiſmatikes, and that therefore they are no true
Church: And thus he ſets them in a worſe eſtate then he places Rome in,
which he now acknowledgeth a true Church: 
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 11.8.</note>According to
his account a Romiſt, a Papiſt, is in a better eſtate for the
conſtitution of their Church, then is the <hi>Ainſworthian.</hi> Rome is
ſpiritually <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Sodome,</hi> as maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> tells vs: that maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> company is not
ſo true a Church as Rome is, and therefore in a worſe eſtate then
<hi>Sodome</hi> or <hi>Egypt,</hi> and conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly are to look for greater
plagues then the plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſorer condemnation then the
fire &amp; brimſtone which was rained from heauen vpon the Sodomites.
Maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> tells them that vnleſſe Rome were a true
Church, their Baptiſme could not be true Baptiſme: Hence it followes that
maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> Church being no true Church, there can bee no
true Baptiſme, but ſuch as are there baptiſed by maſter
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> are to be re-baptiſed: Though the Infants baptiſed in
Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or in Rome are not to be re-baptiſed, yet the
<hi>Ainſworthians</hi> muſt; The practiſe of this is to be expected when
any Infants come with the reuolting parents from the <hi>Ainſworthians</hi>
vnto the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who vnto them muſt become
<hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> Againe, maſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> ordinarie
ſpeech, occaſioned by the Schiſme and departure of maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> people from him, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That God ſtands
with his fanne in his hand, and that God would purge his floore, and take the
chaffe from the wheat: Thus he noteth maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> company to
be but <hi>Droſſe,</hi> and as <hi>Chaffe</hi> for the fire; the reaſon
why he thus ſets his teeth vpon them, is, becauſe they forſooke him, in
that he hath changed his gouernment. And ſince that time he hath ſpoken of
them as of the vncircumciſed Philiſtims, comparing them to <hi>Gath</hi>
and <hi>Askalon</hi> vpon this occaſion of reprouing ſome of vs, for
keeping company with ſome of maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> people, ſaying
we had declared the wickedneſſe of <hi>Studley</hi> in <hi>Gath</hi> and
<hi>Aſhkalon;</hi> vpon this occaſion they may put him in mind of his 
<note n="*" place="margin">Anſw. to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Whites</hi>
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Reader. p. 1.2.</note>words concerning maſter <hi>White,</hi>
they may tell him of the <hi>two ſorts of aduerſaries which the Church
hath: The one of <pb n="72" facs="tcp:22763:41"/> ſuch as be without: the other of ſuch
as ariſe from within the Church it ſelfe. Both heauie enemies: but the
latter farre more grieuous, many wayes:</hi> They may further proceed and ſay
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in his owne words which he vſeth againſt M. <hi>White, Of late
hath riſen vp one</hi> Francis Iohnſon <hi>despitefully reuiling vs, and
wickedly blaſpheming the name and Tabernacle of the Lord. A man that was
himſelfe heretofore not onely a ioyned member, but alſo a Miniſter among
vs, and hath often in our publike meeting before vs all, with his owne mouth,
teſtified his conſent with vs, in the faith which we ſtill profeſſe,
from which he is now reuolted, and of which he is become a notable
aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, ſetting himſelfe tooth and naile (what he can) againſt vs
and our cauſe: and that both priuately and publikely, as now himſelfe hath
manifested to the world. So as himſelfe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> alſo did ſo reaſon againſt
M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their gouernment, that maſter
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> hath oft told him, he did ouerthrow the conſtitution of
their Church: and maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> hath ſo written vnto him, that
with his new grounds hee would ouerthrow the conſtitution of their Church;
which writing being openly read in their meeting-houſe: maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> hath thereupon ſaid, let maſter <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
then looke to the conſtitution of his Church: And this being ſo; muſt
they not of neceſſity thinke his teeth to be as kniues and ſwords, that
doth ſo without pitie deuour the conſtitution of their Church?</p>
                  <p>And moreouer, maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> hath declared
maſter <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths</hi> people to be ſo wilfully blind, and deafe,
and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the fatneſſe of obſtinacie in their erroneous
courſe, that hee applied and denounced againſt them that fearefull and
terrible propheſie, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.25.26.27. yea he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that it
was Gods ſpeciall prouidence once more to bring againe maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> people after they had depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him, that they might
heare that heauie rebuke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto them: And therefore while hee gaue them
ſuch memorable farewell, how can they deny but that his tongue was as a
ſharpe ſword to conſume them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:22763:41"/>Further, whereas there is but one Elder
<hi>de Cluſe</hi> that went with M. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> when he carried
away the Church from the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> what doe the
<hi>Franciſcans</hi> ſay of him? It is teſtified of him by <hi>Iacob
Iohnſon</hi> now an Elder with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Francis Iohnſon,</hi> as
alſo by <hi>M. M.</hi> that he is a notable drunkard, yea ſuch a drunkard,
ſo farre oppreſſed with drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that he hath bin ſcarce able to go;
and as his body hath bin oppreſt, ſo his mind &amp; vnderſtanding alſo,
inſomuch that <hi>Iacob Iohnſon</hi> admoniſhing him of his drunkennes,
hee was not capable of his admonition, but began to talke of other matters,
<hi>viz.</hi> How fit <hi>Iacob Iohnſon</hi> would be for the Paſtor of a
church, &amp;c. what purity is to be expected in that church, where he that
ſhould be che chiefe is ſo ſcandalous, where there is but one gouerning
Elder, and he a drunkard? How bewitched are thoſe people, that ſeeking
purity doe ioyne to ſuch pollution? Thus do the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> by
their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſet their teeth vpon the <hi>Ainſworthians;</hi> but
what ſay they to maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> and his companie? whereas
maiſter <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> in his booke doth vainely boaſt of the
beauteous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of their Church againſt maiſter <hi>Barnard</hi> in
theſe ſame words; 
<note place="margin">Iohn Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons anſwer to R.B. p. 212.
213.</note>
                     <hi>But for our ſelues Maſter</hi> Barnard, <hi>and that whereof
we take experience in this our popularity, as you terme it; I tel you, that if
euer I ſaw the beuty of Sion, &amp; the glory of God filling his tabernacle,
it hath been in the manifeſtation of the diuers graces of God in the Church
in that heauenly harmony &amp; comly order, wherein by the grace of God we are
ſet and walke: wherein if your eies had but ſeene the brethrens ſober and
modest carriage one towards an other, their humble and willing ſubmiſsion
vnto their guides in the Lord, their tender compaſsion towards the weake,
their feruent zeale against ſcandalous offendors, and their long ſuffering
towardes all, you would (I am perſwaded) change your mind, and be compelled
to take vp your parable and bleſſe where you purpoſed to curſe, as</hi>
Balaam <hi>did,</hi> Num. 23. <hi>But whatſoeuer you and all others doe,
theſe our experimentall com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forts, neyther you, nor any other ſhall take
from vs.</hi> Whereas maſter <hi>Smith</hi> alſo in his booke doth vainly
boaſt againſt the <pb n="74" facs="tcp:22763:42"/> ſame M. <hi>Bern,</hi> and being
in the ſame order of popularity with M. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> ſaying; 
<note place="margin">Iohn Smiths paralell p 70.</note>
                     <hi>O
M.</hi> Ber. <hi>if you knew but the comfort and power of Gods ordinances, of
admonition &amp; excommunication, as we do (bleſſed be God) in ſome
meaſure, and that reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is in ſome of vs therby you would be
ſo wonderfully ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed with the power of Gods ordinances, as you would
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the church to be terrible as an army with baners, &amp; yet
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable, louely comly &amp; beutifull: inſomuch as Chriſt ſaith, that
the loue of the church is faire, ſhe wounds his hart with one of hir eies
&amp;c.</hi> Touching both theſe boaſters of their popular go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment
&amp; eſtate, conſider the Iudgement and Sentence of maſter
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> who hath often times paſſed this cenſure vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them,
that the order of popularity which they pleade for is, <hi>The confuſion
of</hi> Korah <hi>and his companie:</hi> often hath hee affirmed in their
publique meeting, that the pretences which they aledge for the power of the
people in iudging of cauſes, are no better than the plea of <hi>Korah,</hi>
when hee ſaid againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron: You take too much
vpon you, ſeeing all the Congregation is holy, euery one of them, and the
Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; wherefore then lift yee your ſelues aboue the
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Lord? Num.</hi> 16.3. Thus doth M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> by
his Sentence obſcure their beauty, and ſtaine the brightneſſe of their
glorie, in ſhewing them to be <hi>Korites, a rebellious route, pleaders for
confuſion, vſurpers riſing vp against</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron;
And in this eſtate, ſeeing the like ſinnes procure the like iudgement,
what can theſe popular <hi>Korites</hi> expect, but as <hi>Korah</hi> for
taking fire in his cenſure was conſumed with fire proceeding from the Lord,
and his followers ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp quick of the earth, which opened hir mouth to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them; euen ſo theſe new <hi>Korites</hi> taking in hand ſuch
fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery cenſures &amp; vnlawfull iudgements ſhould alſo be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
with the fire of their vniuſt cenſures and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; &amp; that
their followers and diſciples ſhould be ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vp quicke, by the
gaping mouth of an earthly, ſenſual, &amp; carnall contention? But M.
<hi>Smith</hi> &amp; M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> inſiſt againſt M.
<hi>Barnard,</hi> alleaging their <hi>experience</hi> &amp; experimentall
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts <pb n="75" facs="tcp:22763:42"/> in their popular eſtate; <hi>Oh M.</hi> Bern.
<hi>if you knew but the comfort</hi> (ſaith M. <hi>Smith</hi>) <hi>if your
eies had but ſeen it,</hi> ſaith M. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon:</hi> wel, to come to
experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with them, M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> may tell them, he hath knowne their
popular order; his eies haue ſeene it, and this, before euer their eies ſaw
it, and with long experience hath he ſeene and conſidered the ſame, yea
in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his experience M. <hi>Smith</hi> &amp; M. <hi>Robinſon</hi>
are but noui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; punies, that came but yeſterday to this practiſe,
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> hath bin long exerciſed: And what ſaith
maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> vpon his fight, knowledge and long experience? He
ſaith not as M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> fooliſhly flatters himſelf, &amp;
imagins that M. <hi>Bern.</hi> would ſpeake and <hi>Take vp his parable to
bleſſe where he purpoſed to curſe as</hi> Balaam. No, M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> takes vp his parable quite contrary; where he once
bleſſed himſelfe &amp; others in that eſtate, he now vpon experience
taks vp his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; curſeth that popular order, by proclaming the
woful fruits therof. And as M <hi>Ber.</hi> makes the ſame to be <hi>the
nurſe of confuſion, the mother of ſchiſme, the breeder of
contention,</hi> euen ſo M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> himſelf now declares it to
be 
<note place="margin">Fra. Iohnſon expoſition of Matth. 18.17.
prefat. p. 1.</note>
                     <hi>a great means &amp; ſpeciall occaſion of ſtrange
opinions &amp; aberations, of lamentable diuiſions, of oppoſing &amp;
despiſing the Elders gouernment, of emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation &amp; debate among people,
with ſundry other euills ariſing &amp; ſpreading themſelues daily, to
the great diſhonor of God, &amp; their owne continuall griefe, and much
reproach from others abroad.</hi> Thus in ſteed of <hi>the glory of the Lord
filling his Tabernacle,</hi> wherof M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> boaſts, M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> tells vs of an horrible confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filling their
meeting-houſe to the great diſhonor of God; Inſteed of the
<hi>manifeſtation of the diuers graces of God,</hi> M. <hi>Ioh.</hi> tells of
the manifeſtation of diuers works of the fleſh &amp; the diuil; inſteed
of heauenly harmony &amp; comly order M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> dreams of, M.
<hi>Iohn</hi> tells of helliſh diſorder, of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge opinions and
aberations; Inſteed <hi>of the brethrens ſober carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> tells of lamentable contentions &amp; diuiſions; Inſteed
of <hi>the humble &amp; willing ſubmiſsion to guides</hi> which M.
<hi>Robinſon</hi> prates of, M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> tells of oppoſing &amp;
deſpiſing the Elders gouernement: and finally, howſoeuer maſter
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> 
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:22763:43"/> tell M. <hi>Bern.</hi> that neither
he, nor any other, ſhall take experimentall comforts from them, yet here we
ſee M. <hi>Iohnſ.</hi> hath taken them away, &amp; by his teſtimony,
which is in this matter much more to bee reſpected than M.
<hi>Robinſons</hi> late experience, theſe experimentall comforts do lie in
the duſt.</p>
                  <p>Againe, whereas M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> diſputeth on this
manner, 
<note place="margin">Iohn Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons anſwer to M B. pa.
170.</note>
                     <hi>Wel, the words are cleare as the Sunne, tell the Church, that
is, the congregation or aſſembly &amp;c.</hi> M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> on the
contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide compares this interpretation to the erroneous expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of
the <hi>Papiſts &amp; Anabaptiſts, inſiſting vpon the letter of the
ſcripture,</hi> peruerting Chriſts words: 
<note place="margin">Fra Iohnſon expoſ of Matt. 18, pref.
pag. 1.</note>
                     <hi>This is my body &amp;c. Teach all nations, and baptiſe them
&amp;c. Sweare not at all; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist not euill &amp;c.</hi> While M.
<hi>Robinſon</hi> accounteth the words <hi>as cleare as the Sun</hi> for his
purpoſe, while M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> counts his interpretation erroneous,
euen as the moſt groſſe, popiſh &amp; anabaptaſticall expoſitions;
what can M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> and his diſciples think of M.
<hi>Iohnſ.</hi> words herein, but that his expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton is as the ſmoake of
that bottomles pit that riſeth to dark their <hi>cleere Sun</hi> with the
groſenes therof? And while M. <hi>Ioh.</hi> like ſuch a locuſt in their
eies obſcures their glorious truth, &amp; hereby declares them to be
<hi>Korites</hi> &amp; the children of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: what can they elſe iudge
of him, but as an horrible ſlanderer? therfore beſides his other
ſlanders, euen in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he is to be reckned amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this
<hi>generation of ſlanderers, whoſe teeth are as ſwords, &amp; their
iawes as kniues &amp;c.</hi> M. <hi>Iohn.</hi> for the further manifeſtation
of M. <hi>Robinſ.</hi> errors ſince that time alſo brought M.
<hi>Robinſ.</hi> book againſt M. <hi>Bern.</hi> into their meeting-houſe,
&amp; there before the congregation made a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne teſtification againſt
the manifold errors contained in it, which he diſclaimed, &amp; not only
ſo, but wrote letters to M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> to rebuke him for the ſame.
<hi>Dan. Studley</hi> the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal. <hi>Franciſcan</hi> is ſo apt in
reproach, that he runs vpon the letter, making as it were an alphabet of
ſlander, hauing it ſo perfect as his <hi>A.B.C</hi> For triall hereof ſee
how he grinds his teeth againſt <hi>Sam. Fuller,</hi> a deacon of M.
<hi>Robinſons</hi> company, whom with his friends he deſcribes as being 
<note n="c" place="margin">The flowers of <hi>Studleyes</hi>
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent letter to <hi>Sam. Fuller.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>ignorant idiots, 
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:22763:43"/> Noddy Nabalites, dogged</hi> Doegs, <hi>fairefaced
Phariſes, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Shemeites, malicious Machiuillians;</hi> Thus
doth this <hi>Alphabeticall ſlanderer</hi> floriſh among them, with the
tanting and flanting figures of his prophane conceited ſpirit. And ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther M.
<hi>Robinſons</hi> company is a cage of vncleane birds, and a knot of vile
perſons, or elſe <hi>Da. Studly</hi> is a notable Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call railer,
which ſets ſuch a range of ſharp teeth vpon them.</p>
                  <p>To conclude and ſeale vp this point of the
<hi>Franciſcan</hi> ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, let the teſtimony of his owne brother
<hi>George</hi> he heere produced againſt him, who witneſſeth of
<hi>Francis</hi> being their Paſtor, that <hi>he</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>George Iohnſ.</hi>
Diſcourſe. page 21.</note> 
                     <hi>changed the voice and tune of a comfortable
ſhepheard to an vnſauory ſcoffing, inueighing, yelling, and cruell
hunting of the ſoules, whom he ought to ſtrengthen and comfort.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, <hi>Habel Iohnſon</hi> tells vs how he rebuked
<hi>Cain Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> openly for 
<note place="margin">Page 34.</note>
                     <hi>peruerting, wreſting,
and abuſing the Scriptures, as alſo for making the pulpit a place to
reuenge himſelfe, and to vomit out his vile and filthy affections:</hi> And
marke what he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>but he neither then, nor yet repenteth thereof,
neither could</hi> George Iohnſon <hi>obtaine of the Church to draw him to
repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: but he hauing with</hi> D. Stud. <hi>once gotten head, he did what
he liſt, &amp; as he liſt.</hi> Further, <hi>Hab. Ioh.</hi> witneſſeth
of the 
<note place="margin">Page 43.</note>
                     <hi>fretting, railing
reuiling, ſcoffing, &amp; flouting vſed by their Paſtor &amp; D.
Stud</hi> And when the Paſtors father ſeparated and ſhewed the cauſes
thereof, then doth this poore <hi>Habel</hi> grone at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof,
and with a wofull <hi>oh</hi> he tells vs, how <hi>they became not onely hot
and warme, but fierce, outragious, and paſsing the bounds of goodneſſe,
ciuilitie and nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If thus they whet the teeth of ſlander againſt their owne
father and brethren, both in the fleſh, and in the faith of the ſeparation,
what wonder if they bite and barke at others?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>PART. 2.</head>
                  <p>COme we in the next place to ſee how the
<hi>Ainſworthians</hi> or old <hi>Browniſts</hi> do whet &amp; ſharpen
their teeth againſt other of the Separatiſts. And here firſt of al, let
vs behold how M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> himſelfe, with ſome other of the
chiefe of his <pb n="78" facs="tcp:22763:44"/> company haue manifeſted maſter
<hi>Iohnſons</hi> Apoſtaſie &amp; back-ſliding from their ancient
Catholike and <hi>Browniſtique</hi> faith, which in former times had been
generally receiued and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by the whole fraternity of all that
ſect: In the ſuit in law, which the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> &amp; the
<hi>Ainſworthians</hi> haue now a long time had before the Iudges and ciuill
Magiſtrates about the meeting-houſe; the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> haue
alleaged that they are the Church, and that therefore they ought to haue the
meeting-houſe which was built for the Church, that M. <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>
&amp; his company were ſchiſmatikes from them, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for their
ſchiſme could not be accounted a true Church, and conſequently had no
right vnto the ſynagogue or mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-houſe: Againe on the other ſide, M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his company haue pleaded that they were the Church,
becauſe they held the ancient faith vpon which their Church was firſt
founded, from which M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his company had fallen away into
Apoſtaſie, and therefore could not be the Church, nor haue any right vnto
the meeting-houſe: M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his people for the
manifeſtation of M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> Apoſtaſie, haue giuen foorth a
writing to ſhew the particular points wherein he hath reuolted: The
occaſion was this. During the time of their ſuite, there were certaine men
deputed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Magiſtrates to heare and examine the cauſe as
arbiters, and if it had been poſſible to haue agreed them; vnto theſe
arbiters did maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> ſide giue in this writing,
wherein it is ſpecified from how many articles of their faith maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his company haue Apoſtated, and how they haue
forſaken both their profeſſion made in their Apologie, and their
confeſſion in their authentique Creed.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="declaration">
                              <head>The articles of his Creed forſaken by M.
<hi>Iohnſon.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>THe words of this declaration taken from the originall
copie which was giuen to the arbiters, are theſe as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
                              <q>
                                 <pb n="79" facs="tcp:22763:44"/> 
                                 <p n="1">1 The 23. article of the confeſsion of our
faith (whereto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo our Apologie agreeth, page 46. 47.) profeſſeth that
euerie Christian congregation hath power to elect and ordaine their owne
ministerie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and vpon deſert againe to depoſe, yea and
excommunicate them. Theſe haue defended that a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, without
Ministers, cannot ordaine officers. And that if the Elderſhip fall into
hereſie or wickedneſſe, the whole Congregation cannot depoſe nor
excommunicate them. And that a Congregation, without an Elderſhip, cannot
excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate any wicked perſon whatſoeuer.</p> 
                                 <p n="2">2 The 24. article (confirmed in our Apologie,
page 60. 62. 63.) profeſſeth that the power to receiue in or to cut off any
mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, is giuen to the whole bodie together of euery Christian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.
<hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe haue pleaded for the
El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip to be the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. and to haue both rightfull
power to excommunicate, though without and againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the
bodie of the Congregation.</p> 
                                 <p n="3">3 The 29. article (as alſo our Apologie,
page 51. 52.) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that the Hierarchie of Archbiſhoppes, Lord
Biſhoppes, Priests, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are a ſtrange and AntiChriſtian
Ministerie and Officers, not inſtituted by Chriſts Teſtament, nor placed
in or ouer his Church. Theſe haue placed ouer them one that was made Prieſt
by a lord Biſhops ordination, ſo as (becauſe of it) they did not ordaine
or impoſe hands on him, when at the ſame time they ordained and impoſed
hands on others, whom together with him they ſet ouer the Church.</p> 
                                 <p n="4">4 The 31. article (and alſo our Apologie,
page 109.) profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that ſuch eccleſiaſticall aſſemblies as
remaine ſo in confuſion and bondage vnder that Antichriſtian
Miniſterie, Courts, Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot bee eſteemed true
viſible Churches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe now pleade not only for them, but
for Rome it ſelfe, to be the true Church of God.</p> 
                                 <p n="5">5 The 32. article (whereto our Apologie
agreeth, page 52. 53. 44.) teſtifieth that all ſuch as haue receiued any of
thoſe falſe offices (of Lord Biſhops, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) are to
giue ouer and leaue them: and ſo hath it been practiſed heere before by all
ſuch <pb n="80" facs="tcp:22763:45"/> Prieſts as came to our faith and Church: now one
is Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ouer them, ordained Prieſt by the Prelates, as is before
ſaid.</p> 
                                 <p n="6">6 The 32. article (which our Apologie alſo
confirmeth, page 45.) profeſſeth that people being come forth of the
Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are willingly to ioyne together in
Chriſtian communion and orderly couenant, and to vnite themſelues vnto
peculiar and viſible congregations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe haue pleaded
that all are bound to communion, by vertue of their Baptiſme recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the
Church of Rome, or other Antichriſtian aſſemblies.</p> 
                                 <p n="7">7 The 33. article (corfirmed alſo in our
apologie, page 46. 47. 48.) profeſſeth that a people ſo ioyned together,
may proceed to choiſe and ordination of officers, except they haue officers
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to do it.</p> 
                                 <p n="8">8 In our apologie, page 113. it was mantained
to be groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and notorious abſurditie, either to hold the
Popiſh Church to be a true Church, hauing a true Miniſterie and true
Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments; or elſe that men are vnbaptiſed, and muſt admit of the
<hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> re-baptiſation. Theſe haue themſelues, much
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to vs, that either the Church and Baptiſme of Rome is true, or
elſe we muſt be re-baptiſed: Both which we ſtill deny.</p> 
                                 <p n="9">9 The 38. article of our confeſsion,
profeſſeth that Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations are by all meanes conuenient to haue the
counſell and helpe one of another in all needfull affaires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
The practiſe of this was denied, when in our greateſt need and trouble they
would not conſent to haue the comfort and helpe of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Church at
Leiden, which profeſſeth the ſame faith with vs.</p> 
                                 <p n="1">1 Before our parting, wee offered, that
notwithſtanding our differences of iudgement, that we would continue
together, if our former practiſe might be retained: but this was
refuſed.</p> 
                                 <p n="2">2 We deſired that then wee might haue
apeaceable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and to be two diſtinct Congregations, each practiſing,
as they were perſwaded; yet nouriſhing brotherly loue and vnitie: This
alſo they would not agree to, vnleſſe wee would leaue this Citie.</p> 
                                 <p n="3">
                                    <pb n="81" facs="tcp:22763:45"/>3 We procured, though
without their conſent, the helpe of the Engliſh Church at Leiden, who
laboured our peace; a way of peace by theſe themſelues propounded, and by
the Church of Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and vs agreed to, theſe after
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>uerſed, and ſtood not vnto,
vnleſſe we would goe dwell out of this Citie. And although in the treatie
of the Agreement it was teſtified by the Elders of that Church, That
vnleſſe it were to the apparant vndoing of vs, and of our families, we
ſhould not be diſmiſſed againe to dwell here: yet becauſe we would
not abſolutely promiſe to leaue this Citie, they would not ſtand to the
agreement which themſelues had made.</p>
                              </q>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thus haue they manifeſted, how M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> hath
forſaken the Faith, and caſt away his old Creede in nine ſpeciall
Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which they haue here numbred out: yea, and beſides that haue
alſo added, in the end thereof, three other articles againſt him and his
companie, wherein they are manifeſted as enemies vnto peace, whereunto they
were ſo deafe to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and not onely that, but alſo are ſhewed to bee
truce-breakers, violaters of their promiſe, and falſifiers of their word,
by reuerſing the way of peace that was once conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and for not
ſtanding vnto the agreement which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had made. And thus by this
writing, and by the twelue articles thereof, nine concerning faith, and three
concerning peace and truth, the <hi>Franciſcanes</hi> are ſhewed to be
without faith, without peace, and without truth. And thus hath Maſter
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> ſet twelue ſharpe teeth vpon the
<hi>Franciſcans,</hi> and thereby made twelue wounds in the bodie of their
honeſtie and faith, vntill with ſome probable anſwere they can ſalue
the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But alas how ſhall M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> with any ſound
anſwer ſalue his faith and his honeſtie, by writing againſt M.
<hi>Ainſworth,</hi> that doth now become his accuſer? Seeing by M.
<hi>Iohnſons</hi> owne teſtimonie and confeſſion M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Fran. Iohnſons</hi> enquirie of
<hi>Tho. Wh. p.</hi> 43.</note> 
                     <hi>for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wiſdome, and
godlineſſe as alſo for his faithfull teaching of the Church, and vpright
walking toward all, is ſo well knowne and approued, as neither he not we need
regard any aduerſaries <pb n="82" facs="tcp:22763:46"/> malice and oppoſition againſt
him.</hi> Theſe things being ſo, what need M. <hi>Ainſworth to regard the
malice and oppoſition of M. Iohnſon</hi> now his aduerſarie, vnleſſe
M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> malice be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the malice of other men, and
vnleſſe his oppoſition be more terrible than the oppoſition of all
aduerſaries beſides? If M. <hi>Ainſworths learning</hi> be ſo <hi>well
knowne and approued,</hi> then what needes he to regard M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi>
ſophiſtrie? If his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be ſo <hi>well knowne and approued,</hi>
what needes he to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the policies and ſubtleties of <hi>Fran.
Iohnſon</hi> and <hi>Dan. Studley?</hi> If his <hi>godlineſſe and vpright
walking towards all be ſo well knowne and approued,</hi> then what great
cauſe hath euerie man to regard the witneſſe of M. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi>
which he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth againſt M. <hi>Iohnſon?</hi> And what cauſe hath M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> to be aſhamed of his wayes, that is accuſed of
Apoſtaſie, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, Error, Falſehood, Lying, and Promiſe-breaking,
and all this by M. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> whom himſelfe doth acknowledge to be
ſo <hi>godly and vpright a walker towards all?</hi> It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as like
that M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> hath now walkt as vprightly towards <hi>Francis
Iohnſon</hi> as he did before towards <hi>Th. Wh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, the <hi>Ainſworthians</hi> ſcoffing at M.
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> now that they haue reiected him, they ſay, That M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> hath long time wrought iourney-worke vnder M.
<hi>Iohnſon,</hi> but that now he ſets vp 
<note n="*" place="margin">The two ſhops of Error and
Schiſme.</note>ſhop for himſelfe, and this vnder M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi>
noſe, their meeting-houſe being the next houſe but one vnto M.
<hi>Iohnſons</hi> ſhop or meeting-houſe. Nay, further they ſay, that M.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> ſeekes to take away M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> ſhop from
ouer his head, while by their ſuit in law they contend for the
meeting-houſe it ſelfe, hoping that M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his
companie ſhall get the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Further, to come vnto more hainous matters, it is
witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome of M. <hi>Ainſworths</hi> companie, <hi>That there
is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murder and approued whoredomes maintained or ſuffered in M.</hi>
Iohnſons <hi>Church.</hi> This hath bin teſtified by <hi>Iohn Trappes.</hi>
M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his Elders alſo do know, that this is auouched
againſt them: for this hath <hi>Iohn Trap</hi> witneſſed vnto their
meſſengers, ſolemnely 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Septemb.</hi> 8.
1611.</note>ſent from their Church, to enquire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <pb n="83" facs="tcp:22763:46"/>
this matter, and hath alſo offered to proue this before the magiſtrates,
yea and hath prouoked them much to bring the matter into queſtion. It is
witneſſed alſo vnto the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of their Church, That M. <hi>de
Cluſe</hi> hearing it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that there was <hi>approued murder
maintained in M.</hi> Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould alſo graunt vnto
the ſame, ſaying, <hi>Yea, it is too true, or it is too true indeed, the
more is the pitie, or the more ſorrie he was, to like effect, &amp;c.</hi>
Are not the teeth of the <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthians</hi> like kniues vnto the
<hi>Franciſcans?</hi> Doe they not cut and bite deepe in ſuch ſpeeches
and teſtimonies which they giue touching the euils that are tolerated or
maintained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them? Are they fit men to ſeparate from all other true
Churches for corruptions, while the charge of ſuch abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is tolerated
among themſelues?</p>
                  <p>To conclude this point, let it be conſidered, that euen then
when M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and M. <hi>Ainſworths</hi> companie were yet one,
long before any ſhew of this great diuiſion that is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, it
came to paſſe, that <hi>Thomas Cocky</hi> and <hi>Iacob Iohnſon,</hi> two
men of note amongſt them, both of them Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, falling into variance one
with another, one of them brings in before the Church a Liſt of fifteene lyes
wherewith he charged the other; the other againe to requite his paines brings
in at the next turne againſt him a Liſt of ſixteene lyes; betwixt them
both they make vp the ſumme of 31 lyes: Is it not a token, that the father of
that Companie is the father of lyes, when as the children thereof are ſo
fruitfull in lyes? Is it probable that the truth of God ſhould be tied and
treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp onely among theſe lying companions, whiles all the true
Churches in the world beſide are not able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the myſterie of
that Separation, which they ſay is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto them? What wonder is it,
that theſe men ſhould raiſe many lies and ſlanders againſt others,
when as thus they heaped them vpon themſelues mutually? And what wonder if
they bite one another now that they are rent in two, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when they were
vndiuided they ſpared not one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:22763:47"/>
                  <head>PART. 3.</head>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> writing in defence of the popular
gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt M. <hi>Bernard,</hi> doth therein vtter many hard
ſpeeches againſt the oppugners thereof. Now M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> being an
oppugner thereof, as well as M. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and vſing the ſame
reaſons that M. <hi>Bernard</hi> doth to that purpoſe, it followes
neceſſarily, that thoſe ſpeeches and rebukes which M.
<hi>Robinſon</hi> layes vpon M. <hi>Bernard,</hi> do through his ſide
pierce and wound M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> alſo, when he holds the ſame opinion
and vſeth the ſame arguments with M. <hi>Bernard.</hi> And this is the
rather to be obſerued, becauſe M. <hi>Ainſworths</hi> people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing
M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> for his not anſwering of M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Expoſ. of <hi>Mat.</hi>
18.</note>booke, they alledge and plead, that M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> hath
anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, &amp; confuted his reaſons in the confutation of M
<hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard;</hi> and therefore the rebukes which in that point and in that
behalfe are layed vpon M. <hi>Bernard,</hi> are many of them alſo to be as
well applyed vnto M. <hi>Iohnſon:</hi> For example</p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Anſwer to M <hi>Bernard, p.</hi>
124.</note> writing, <hi>That their practiſe is anſwerable to their
profeſsion,</hi> and ſhewing their profeſſion what it is, from the
confeſſion of their faith, <hi>Artic.</hi> 24. inferreth from thence, that
they cannot be charged with <hi>baſtardly runagates.</hi> But on the
contrarie ſide, M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> (as is noted in the former Section)
declaring that M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> is fallen from their faith euen in that
very article, it followeth hereupon from M. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſons</hi> ſpeech,
that M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his companie forſaking that profeſsion of
faith, are therefore to be deemed <hi>baſtardly runagates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> affirming, That they are 
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
152.</note>
                     <hi>miſerable guides,</hi> which teach, that the power of the
keyes is giuen to the chiefe officers, ſhewing alſo, that it is 
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 153.</note>
                     <hi>erronious
and deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie</hi> to the nature of the Goſpell and free donation of
Chriſt thus to impropriate and ingroſſe the keyes; He doth hereby declare
M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and M. <hi>Clyfton</hi> to be miſerable Guides: yea,
that they are ſacrilegious <hi>ingroſſers of the keyes,</hi> contrarie 
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22763:47"/> to the nature of the Goſpel and free donation of
Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they teach that doctrine aſwell as maſter
<hi>Barnard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Anſwer to M. <hi>Bernard, p.</hi>
160.</note>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> reproouing the enuious dealing of them that
oppugne popularitie, for arrogating al the power of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into their
hands, doth declare this by alleadging of 1. <hi>Ki.</hi> 22.24. and hereby it
followes vpon his reproofe, that maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and maiſter
<hi>Clifton,</hi> holding the point with maiſter <hi>Bernard,</hi> are alſo
like the arrogant and prowd <hi>Zidkiah,</hi> that ſmote the Lords Prophet on
the cheeke. Thus is maiſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> noted as a cruell
perſecutor, making himſelfe to be 
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 162.</note>
                     <hi>thought
all eie from top to bottome,</hi> and making his people in the meane time to be
a <hi>blinde beetle,</hi> euen <hi>ſtone-blinde, that cannot ſee one
ſteppe before them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> reproouing maiſter <hi>Bernard,</hi>
for alleadging the charge of Princes and Eccleſiaſticall Gouernours
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doth blame him herein, as though hee lai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> a 
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 164.</note>
                     <hi>Corner
ſtone of Babylon</hi> hereby: now maiſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> yoaking
theſe Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall officers together in this 
<note n="c" place="margin">Expoſit of <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.
<hi>Reu.</hi> 3.</note>allegation alſo doth hereby incurre the ſame rebuke,
and is heereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his account, <hi>a builder of Babylon,</hi> as well as
maiſter <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> imputeth vnto maiſter
<hi>Bernard,</hi> the occaſion of a ſtrange and new kinde of 
<note n="d" place="margin">Anſwer to M <hi>Bernard, p.</hi>
234</note>
                     <hi>Schiſme,</hi> for teaching, that the power of Excommunication
is in the Officers; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (ſaith he) <hi>All the communion paſſeth
betwixt the parties admoniſhing and admoniſhed, excommunicating and
excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, whereof the body of the Church is neither, but a very cipher
and a hang-by:</hi> Now maiſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> practiſing and teaching
that which maiſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> here reprooueth, by his Sentence is
become guiltie of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> making his Church to be a <hi>cypher and
a hang-by.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> ſpeaking of the power of binding and
loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſaith; 
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 244.</note>
                     <hi>Theſe knots
are to bee tyed and looſed onely by the Chauncellours or Officialls fingers,
this power haue they enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with hedge and ditch &amp;c.</hi> This
contumely may as iuſtly be returned vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> head
with maſter <hi>Robinſons</hi> 
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:22763:48"/> wordes, that thoſe
knots are to be tyed and looſed onely by maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his
officials fingers, eſpecially the filthie fingers of <hi>Dan. Studley</hi>
his 
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quondam.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>chiefe
Chancelor,</hi> and that hee hath captiued his Church, and ſeized the
ſubſtance and ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, as it were, into their hands, leauing the poore
people onely the ſhell and ſhadow to feede vpon.</p>
                  <p>Further, maſter <hi>Bernard</hi> writing about ordination
and ſucceſſion of the Miniſterie, is tasked by maſter
<hi>Robinſon</hi> as being 
<note n="b" place="margin">Anſwere to <hi>Ber.</hi> pag.
421.</note>
                     <hi>either a marked ſeruant of the Pope, or one that cared not
what he wrote for ſome preſent ſeeming aduantage.</hi> Now maſter
<hi>Iohnſon</hi> arguing in like matter about ordination and ſucceſſion
of the Miniſterie, and fetching the ſame from Rome, the reproach doth fall
as ſtrangely vpon maſter <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> pate. Maſter
<hi>Robinſon</hi> writing about the Temples wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we worſhip Saints, that
they are as 
<note n="c" place="margin">Page 443.</note>
                     <hi>execrable things
to be auoided,</hi> and yet further ſaith, that they are the leaſt 
<note n="d" place="margin">Page 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.</note> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt him and maſter <hi>Ber.</hi> The
matter therefore of popular gouernment and the peoples power, is acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
to be a matter of greater waight, and therin maſter <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
erring, falles into a ſinne more then <hi>execrable or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To omit many the like ſpeeches, by this it doth euidently
appeare how maſter <hi>Robinſons</hi> teeth are like kniues, and his iawes
like ſwords to eate vp maſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> companie, while he thus
bites them by his doctrine, while hee makes maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and his
elders to be <hi>bastardly runnagates; miſerable guides; engroſſers of
the keyes; arrogant Zidkiahs, laying the corner ſtone of Babylon; Lucians or
skoffing Atheists; Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, making their Church a Cypher and a hang-by;
wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an honeſt heart; like Chancellors and Officials captiuing of the
Church; either marked ſeruants of the Pope; or ſuch as care not what they
ſay for ſome preſent ſeeming aduantage; v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a power more then
execrable or accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus hauing ſhewed what he writeth againſt maſter
<hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> let vs ſee in a word what hee witneſſeth againſt
maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> companie. When ſome of maſter
<hi>Ainſworths</hi> 
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:22763:48"/> companie wrote vnto maſter
<hi>Robinſon,</hi> deſiring him to come and helpe the Lord againſt the
mightie (againſt maſter <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whom they had accounted as the
ſtrongeſt Giant of the Separation) maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> at laſt
came vnto them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> about the change
of his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and being come and entred within the liſtes of that
diſputation, he found maſter <hi>Ainſworths</hi> faction ſo
diſorderly and clamorous, that he often deſired them to be ſtill and
ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and reproued their vnſeemely and vnreaſonable beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior: but at
length when he ſaw the tumult encreaſe, (loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon them round about, as
a man amazed and agaſt, with fierce and outragious carriage) he did then
openly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie among them, <hi>That he had rather walke in peace with fiue
godly perſons, than to liue with fiue hundred or fiue thouſand ſuch
vnquiet perſons as theſe were.</hi> Hauing ſpoken to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> told him further, That this was a ſmall thing,
and nothing in reſpect of their vnpeaceable and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered carriage at
ſome other times. And theſe things being ſo, alas how euill doe they
prouide for their owne peace and comfort, which ioyne themſelues vnto ſuch
a contentious and tumultuous band of Schiſmatikes?</p>
                  <p>As for maſter <hi>Smith</hi> and his diſciples, they doe
at once as it were with open mouth ſwallow vp all the Separation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
by 
<note n="a" place="margin">Charact of Beaſt.
Epiſtle</note>
                     <hi>proteſting againſt their falſe conſtitution,
falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, falſe Miniſterie, and falſe Gouernment.</hi> For
howſoeuer maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> did heretofore ſeeme to agree with
maſter <hi>Smith</hi> in the reproofe of the <hi>triformed Presbiterie,</hi>
as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it, and hath had much queſtion with his people about the
ſame; howſoeuer maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> hath followed maſter
<hi>Smith</hi> in his doctrine and practiſe about <hi>the ſeparation in
almes,</hi> and ſo hath one ſpeciall kind of ſeparation more than
maſter <hi>Iohnſon</hi> or maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> in their Companies
doe practiſe, and therefore might ſeeme to haue a more holy treaſurie,
and a more pure ſacrifice of almes, free from that rigour and pollution
wherewith the treaſurie of the <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes</hi> and
<hi>Ainſworthians</hi> appeares to be defiled: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22763:49"/> all this, while they retaine a falſe conſtitution,
mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Smith</hi> ſtil proteſteth againſt them all without
exception, 
<note n="b" place="margin">Epiſtle to the
Character.</note>
                     <hi>That there is no one true ordinance of the Lord among
them:</hi> And how they haue on the other ſide laied him open, as a
<hi>Schiſmatike, an Heretike, and an Apoſtata,</hi> their Bookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him doe plenteouſly declare.</p>
                  <p>We might here proceed yet further to ſhew, what bitings
there be among the other leſſer factions and broken peeces of the
ſeparation, and among thoſe that walke alone; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alreadie led the
Reader a rough way, and beeing our ſelues weary thereof, wee doe here reſt
our ſelues, and ſit downe for the preſent, hoping that this which is
alreadie done wil be ſufficient to ſhew what bitter fruit groweth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the
trees of the ſeparation; and withall, deſiring the Lord to keepe his
ſeruants from taſting of this forbidden fruit, which in our owne experience
we haue felt ſo bitter, we here take our leaue, and heartily bid the
Chriſtian Reader farewell in the Lord.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <epigraph>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATTH. 7.15.16.</bibl> 
               <p>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in ſheepes
clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but inwarly they are rauening wolues.</p> 
               <p>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits. Do men gather grapes of
thornes, or figges of thiſtles.</p>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
